<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Catholick schismatology, or, An account of schism and schismaticks in the several ages of the world : to which are prefixed some remarks on Mr. Bolde's plea for moderation / J.B.</title>
            <author>J. B. (J. Browne)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 209 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 105 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29830</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5116</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37483</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16963039</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16963039</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105495</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29830)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105495)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1610:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Catholick schismatology, or, An account of schism and schismaticks in the several ages of the world : to which are prefixed some remarks on Mr. Bolde's plea for moderation / J.B.</title>
                  <author>J. B. (J. Browne)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 119, [1], 78 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Anthony Steevens ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Browne by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Contains bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bold, S. --  (Samuel), 1649-1737. --  Plea for moderation towards dissenters.</term>
               <term>Schism --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105495:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Catholick Schiſmatology: OR, An ACCOUNT OF SCHISM AND SCHISMATICKS: IN The ſeveral Ages of the World. To which are prefixed ſome Remarks on Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi>'s Plea for Moderation.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Eccl. 2.</hi>
                  </bibl> Wo to them that have a double heart— and to the Sinner that goteh two manner of ways</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Auguſtini Epiſt. 166.</hi>
                  </bibl> 
                  <hi>Lett. G. Conſtantinus</hi> contra partem <hi>Donati</hi> ſeveriſſimam legem dedit, hunc imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati Filii ejus talia praeceperunt; Quibus ſuccedens <hi>Julianus</hi> deſertor Chriſti &amp; inimicus — libertatem Parti <hi>Donati</hi> permiſit &amp; reddidit baſilicas— eo modo putans Chriſtianum nomen poſſe perire de terris.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>J. B.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Anthony Steevens,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>OXON</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:105495:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105495:2"/>
            <head>To the Worſhipful ROBERT FOLEY <abbr>
                  <hi>Eſq</hi>
               </abbr> One of His MAJESTIES Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of the Peace for the County of <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Worſhip,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>'TIS not long, ſince thruſting ſuch Books as this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Preſs, was like thruſting ones hand in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a neſt of Hornets; when
<pb facs="tcp:105495:3"/>
neither Innocence, nor Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, nor any thing that's ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred, could be ſufficient Fence againſt the pungent and veno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Detractions of a waſpiſh ſort of Sectaries. And then indeed it was but needful, in behalf of ſuch Books as this, to ask the Patronage of ſome ſuch as your ſelf; whoſe ſtanch Loyalty in the late diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing and perilous times, thoſe days of Danger and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke, was yet ſo truly Heroick, as to dare to look Faction in the face, and oppoſe it even then, when moſt Inſolent and Domineering. A practice on grounds of Reaſon ſo truly Generous; on grounds of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity ſo Religious, as
<pb facs="tcp:105495:3"/>
makes your late Promotion, a due Debt to your Merit, as your Merit is to your ſelf. But now bleſſed be God, that by wonted Miracle of Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, has <hi>made the King great in his Salvation;</hi> has in great meaſure given him the Hearts of his Subjects, and <hi>the Necks of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies;</hi> has <hi>turned our threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Captivity back;</hi> and made our <hi>Engliſh Zion</hi> like to be <hi>the praiſe of the whole Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that now the deſign of this Dedication, is cheifly this, To publiſh to the World my grateful acknowledgment of your great Favours, preſuming that the good deſign of this
<pb facs="tcp:105495:4"/>
little Book, will help to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie for its great defects; eſpecially, if it be interpreted, as Divines interpret Parables, <hi>Quae non ſunt argumenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ultra ſuum Scopum:</hi> The Scope or Intention of it, being no more than ſuch an imperfect Schiſmatology, as may inſtruct but the vulgar Reader, in ſome little of that great agreement between the Modern Schiſmaticks, and thoſe of Old; which I take to be a Novel expedient, whereby to endeavour (as every honeſt man ought) the expoſal of that pernicious Sin of Schiſm, the depluming of that Church mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of all ſuch thieviſh Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, and popular Decoy, as
<pb facs="tcp:105495:4"/>
erroneous conſcienciouſneſs, and ſpecious Pretenſions to Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty beyond holier Perſons than themſelves; to expoſe this vile Sin to the publik view (like <hi>Aeſops</hi> Crow) to be reviled and hooted at, as the very peſt of Societies, and bane of Chriſtianity, fatal to Churches and Kingdoms, deteſtable and odious to God and Good Men; worſe (ſaid the Fathers) than<note n="a" place="margin">Dionyſ. ap. Euſeb. <hi>l.</hi> 6.</note> Idolatry,<note n="b" place="margin">Opt. l. 1.</note> Sacriledg, or<note n="c" place="margin">Chryſoſt. ad. Eph. <hi>p.</hi> 823.</note> Hereſie, and yet now a days ſo little made Conſcience of. This is chiefly the deſign of this little Book, and my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments to your Worſhip is the deſign of its Dedication; as alſo to beg the encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your Worſhips Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation;
<pb facs="tcp:105495:5"/>
and to contribute a wiſh to the long continuance of your happineſs here, and the compleatment of it here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after; which is, honoured Sir, the hearty prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Thankful and Obedient, as much Obliged Servant, <hi>J. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:105495:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Catholick Schiſmatology: OR,</hi> An Account of Schiſm and Schiſmaticks in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Ages of the World.</head>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The Introduction.</head>
               <p>THO the firſt two thouſand years of the World, called the <hi>Patriarchal</hi> Ages, [<hi>which was from the Creation, to the giving of the Law to</hi> Moſes] were called by the <hi>Jewiſh Rabbies,</hi> the two thouſand years of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:105495:6"/>
emptineſs; becauſe of that little that is recorded of the Tranſactions of thoſe times; yet is not the Holy Scripture ſilent in this matter, but ſpeaks of <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> as coaeval with Sin and Satan: St. <hi>Jude</hi> ſpeaking of the Separatiſts of his time the <hi>Gnoſtick-Schiſmaticks,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jude 6.</note> compares them firſt to the fallen Angels, the firſt that ſinned; thoſe Schiſmaticks from the Church tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant, <hi>Jude</hi> 6. Where he plainly intimates, That as the Devil was the firſt Sinner, ſo was he the firſt Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick: Saies the Apoſtle, <hi>The firſt that left his first eſtate,</hi> which was Communion with the Church triumphant.</p>
               <p>From this he deſcends to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them to ſome of the firſt Schiſmaticks from the Church Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant. He inſtances firſt in <hi>Cain,</hi> Jude 11. <hi>They have gone in the way of Cain;</hi> or which is all one, they have followed the Principle and Practiſe of <hi>Cain, i. e.</hi> are <hi>Cainites.</hi> As thoſe that go in the way of, or
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105495:6"/>
follow the Principles and Practiſe of <hi>Aerius, Donatus, Novatus,</hi> are called <hi>Aerians, Donatiſts, Novatians.</hi> And thus do ſome of the moſt learned Nonconformiſts interpreat thoſe words, <hi>The way of</hi> Cain,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Manton,</hi> and Mr <hi>Jen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins</hi> Expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on <hi>Jude.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>i e.</hi> ſay they, the way of <hi>Cains</hi> Separation. Cain <hi>was the firſt Separatiſt (ſaies Dr.</hi> Manton) <hi>He went out from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord, that is, from the Church</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>where the preſence of Gods Grace is.</hi> And therefore <hi>Cains</hi> example is produced, becauſe <hi>(ſaies that Expoſitor)</hi> he was the firſt and chief of thoſe that departed from the true Church and pure Service of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>KORAHITES.</head>
               <p>THus ſaies the Apoſtle of the Separatiſts of his time, <hi>Jud.</hi> 11. <hi>They have periſhed in the gainſaying of Korah.</hi> This <hi>Korah</hi> was one of the Sons of <hi>Levi,</hi> of great eſteem among the People, and great inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105495:7"/>
in many of the Princes; and (no doubt) was accounted an able and godly man; only thus, he was a factious <hi>Levite,</hi> diſſenting and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> the King and the Prieſt, was his only fault. Whoever conſults the Hiſtory of Schiſmaticks from the times of the Apoſtles, to this preſent Age, and compares them with the Modern ones in their profeſſed op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, as well to the Monarchical as Epiſcopal Government, muſt give them Extraction from this famous Triumvirate <hi>Korah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aeri.</hi> Red. Preface.</note> combined in an Aſſociation againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Prince, and the High Prieſt. <hi>Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> deſcending from the line of <hi>Reuben,</hi> the eldeſt Son of <hi>Jacob,</hi> thought themſelves more worthy of the Sovereign Power than <hi>Moſes,</hi> who deſcended from the younger Houſe; and <hi>Korah</hi> thought himſelf ſo much neglected in ſeeing <hi>Elizaphen,</hi> the Son of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziel,</hi> made Prince of the <hi>Koha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thites,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105495:7"/>
[The principal Family of the</hi> Levites <hi>next to that of</hi> Gerſon] when he himſelf deſcended of the eldeſt Brother, and therefore thought that if there were not a Parity, but an <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> among the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Miniſters, that himſelf was as fit for the chief Prieſthood as <hi>Aaron.</hi> Hereupon having compared their grievances, they reſolved on a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy, and that neither Sovereign Prince, nor chief Prieſt ſhould Lord it over them, but rather that a <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Parity ſhould be both in Sacred and Civil Matters: Upon this they preſently formed their party, drew into the Conſpiracy no leſs than 250 of the chief men of the Aſſembly, and with them boldly appear againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron;</hi> telling them to their faces, that they took too much upon them, that all the Lords people were holy; and that therefore they ought not to lift up themſelves above the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation. Now tho ſome of the chief Princes of the houſe of <hi>Dan,</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:105495:8"/>
did appear in the Conſpiracy; yet it is plainly called in Scripture, the <hi>gainſaying of Korah,</hi> becauſe chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly carried on by the intereſt and credit that he had among the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; particularly on the account of his pretended Zeal for the Worſhip of God,<note place="margin">Joſeph. Antiq. <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> and his great pretence to the good of the Commonwealth. But a factious <hi>Levite</hi> he was; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting and murmuring againſt the King and the Clergy, was his great and only fault. In the head of a numerous Faction, he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to ſtone <hi>Moſes,</hi> and (as <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephus</hi> ſaies) ran with great Noiſe and Uproar, crying before the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle of God, That the Tyrant <hi>(Moſes)</hi> was to be cut off, and the People deliver'd from Bondage; and the like outcrys of Property and Priviledg againſt Prerogative and Arbitrary Government. <hi>By ſuch Sedition</hi> (ſaies Mr. <hi>Jenkins) to throw</hi> Aaron <hi>out of the Prieſthood, and gain it to himſelf, and with</hi> Dathan <hi>and</hi> Abiram, <hi>to depoſe</hi> Moſes
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105495:8"/>
                  <hi>from the civil Government, and take it to themſelves. St.</hi> Jude<hi>'s purpoſe here is to ſhew</hi> (ſaies that great <hi>Nonconformiſt) that ſuch ſeducing</hi> Separatiſts, <hi>as theſe</hi> Gnoſticks,<note place="margin">Expoſition on the place.</note> 
                  <hi>are Enemies not only to Eccleſiaſtical, but Civil Order and Superiority.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And this example of</hi> Korah <hi>is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced</hi> (ſaith Dr. <hi>Manton) as to note the factious Practices of Seducers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Expoſition on the place.</note> 
                  <hi>ſo alſo Gods vengeance on all ſuch; they were factious againſt</hi> Moſes <hi>and</hi> Aaron, <hi>and they periſhed in their attempt, and ſo will all they that riſe up againſt Magiſtracy and Miniſtry, as ſure</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>as if it were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready accompliſhed.</hi> And the other Nonconformiſt-Expoſitor in his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, <hi>How miraculouſly did ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance overtake</hi> Korah <hi>and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany</hi> [for their Schiſm and Sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on] <hi>the Earth clave and ſwallowed them up for making a cleft (or Schiſm) in the Congregation: and after that two hundred and fifty of their Princes, Men of Renown, were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed by a fire from the Lord; and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105495:9"/>
after that, fourteen thouſand and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven hundred were ſlain by the Plague.</hi> And this St. <hi>Jude</hi> apply's to ſuch Chriſtians as ſeparate themſelves, as deſpiſe Dominion, and ſpeak evil of Dignities; that renounce the Authority and Communion of the Church; of ſuch as theſe he ſaies, they periſh'd in the <hi>gainſaying of</hi> Korah.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>PHARISEES.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THey were a moſt zealous and ſtrict Sect above all others of the</hi> Jewiſh <hi>Religion; and were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> Phariſees <hi>from their Separation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> From <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſeparavit, ſecrevit, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſit; quaſi ſequeſtrato ab aliis vita religioſiri; <hi>becauſe ſeparated from others to a more ſtrict way of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing Religion.</hi> Paſor <hi>cites</hi> Heſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius,<note place="margin">Lexi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>for making</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, i. e. <hi>Phariſee, a Divider, a Separatiſt, a Puritan, all one; but the primary ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105495:9"/>
of the word</hi> Phariſee <hi>is</hi> [one that ſeparates.]</p>
               <p>Joſephus, <hi>tho himſelf a</hi> Jew,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Antiq. Judaic.</hi> l. 17. l. 13. c. 23. <hi>&amp; paſſim</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and ſometime a</hi> Phariſee, <hi>gives this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of them,</hi> That they were a crafty and ſubtil Generation of men, that imployed their power mightily in oppoſing Kings; that had inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated themſelves ſo far into the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and eſteem of the populacy, that their good or bad word was able to make or blaſt any one with the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; let their report be never ſo falſe and malicious. And therefore <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander Jannaeus,</hi> when he lay a dying, adviſed the Queen his wife, as ever ſhe regarded her ſafety, by all means to comply with them, and to pretend to govern by their Councel and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; affirming that his offending that ſort of men, was that which derived the Odium of the Nation upon him, and was the greateſt cauſe of his fatal miſcarriage. Certain it is, that they were prodigiouſly proud and ſelf conceited, cenſorious and ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natured; that they hated all mankind
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105495:10"/>
but themſelves; and whoever would not be of their way, they cenſured as a Reprobate and a Villian; exceeding zealous they were to make Proſelytes to their Party, confining all Religion and Kindneſs within the bounds of their own party. <hi>Like the</hi> Donatiſts <hi>their Followers, that were the moſt grievous ſort of Perſecutors, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they got power, and yet cried out moſt againſt Perſecution, Matt. 23.4.</hi> They bound on mens ſhoulders heavy burdens, and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous to be born; <hi>yet inveigh bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> against it in others, <hi>verſ. 30.</hi> If we had lived in the days of our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers, we would not have been par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers with them in the blood of the Prophets. <hi>On which very account Chriſt calls them Serpents,</hi> verſ. <hi>33. a ſubtil inſinuating Generation of men, full of Folds and Intreagues, that would put on the appearance of greateſt Mortification, and Self-denyal, and Holineſs; yet were (ſaies Chriſt in that very verſe) Vipers,</hi> A generation of Vipers, <hi>for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105495:10"/>
their abominable cruelty: The firſt Principles wherewith they inſpired their new Converts (as</hi> Joſephus <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates) were,</hi> That none but they were the Godly party; and that all other Perſon were but Slaves and Sons of the Earth, and therefore endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd, eſpecially to inſpire them with a mighty Zeal and Fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt all that differ'd from them. To this end they were wont not only to ſeparate, but diſcriminate themſelves from the Community, by ſome peculiar Notes and Badges of Diſtinction, ſuch as their long Robes, and broad Phylacteries, their large Fringes and Borders of their Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Their dogged and ill-natured principles, together with their Seditious and uncharitable Behaviour, they endeavoured to palliate and varniſh over, with a more than ordinary pretence and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Religion: Such Duties eſpecially as did immediately refer to God and his Worſhip; as frequent faſting and praying, which they did
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105495:11"/>
very oft, and very long, with demure and mortified looks, in a whining and affected tone, and this almoſt in every corner of the ſtreets: <hi>Thus</hi> Joſephus <hi>of the</hi> Phariſees, Antiq. Judaic.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>ZEALOTS.</head>
               <p>THE <hi>Zealots</hi> were a Sect or Branch of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> who looked upon themſelves as the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors of <hi>Elias, Samuel,</hi> and others of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Worthies, but eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <hi>Phineas;</hi> which Worthies living under a perfect Theocracy, had the miraculous impulſe and guidance of Gods Spirit, immediate Direction and Commiſſion from God for what they did; and particularly in ſuch Acts as thoſe of <hi>Phineas [tho no Magiſtrate]</hi> his killing <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Cosbi; Samuel</hi>'s <hi>killing Agag,</hi> &amp;c. And in imitation of theſe, the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105495:11"/>
                  <hi>Jewiſh Zealots</hi> miſtaking a Diaboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Suggeſtion for ſupernatural Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation; a boiling Paſſion for holy Zeal; and a wild Imagination for holy Divine motion, pretended a Commiſſion from Heaven for the moſt horrid and deteſtable under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings, ſuch as rebelling againſt Princes, Aſſaſſinating Nobles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in pretence for the Honour and Glory of God.</p>
               <p>The account Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> gives of them, is briefly thus,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Annotat. on</hi> 1 Pet. 4.15. <hi>Lett. G.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>The</hi> Jewiſh Zealots <hi>pretending to a perpetual im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity from all humane Power,</hi> [as being the only Children of God, and upon that account, to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to no men, eſpecially Heathens, but to enjoy an <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or perfect immunity] <hi>would force all men to joyn with them againſt the</hi> Romans, <hi>i. e. The publick peace; calling them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors and Saviours of the Nation, and plundering all that would not be as Seditious as themſelves, under pretence of Zeal for the Law of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105495:12"/>
God, and making all men perform their duty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Agreeable to this, is that of Dr. <hi>Cave [in the life of St.</hi> Simon <hi>the</hi> Zealot] from <hi>Maimonides, Joſephus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>They were</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>a Sect of the</hi> Phariſees, <hi>mighty Aſſertors of the Law, and of the ſtrictneſs and puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the</hi> Jewiſh <hi>Religion, aſſuming a Liberty to themſelves to queſtion (and puniſh) notorious Offenders, without ſtaying for the formality of the Law; and (when they thought good) executing capital Vengeance on them. Thus</hi> (ſaies my Author from <hi>Maimonides) when a Blaſphemer curſed God by the name of any Idol, the next</hi> Zealot <hi>that met him, had power to kill him, without bringing him before the</hi> Sanhedrim. <hi>Thus in imitation of</hi> Phineas (<hi>who in a great paſſion for the Honour of God, did immediate Execution on</hi> Zimri <hi>and</hi> Cosbi) <hi>they took upon them to execute Judgment in extraordinary Cauſes, and that (at firſt) not only by the Connivence, but good leave of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105495:12"/>
Rulers and People, till in after-times under a pretence of this, their Zeal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated into all manner of Licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and wild Extravagance, and they not only became the very peſt of the Commonwealth at home, but open'd the door for the</hi> Romans <hi>to invade them to their final ruin. They were continually prompting the people ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditiouſly to throw off the</hi> Roman <hi>Yoke, to vindicate themſelves into their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Liberty</hi> [excelling the <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees</hi> in their outcrys for property and priviledg againſt their Rulers Prerogative] <hi>and when they had turned all things into hurry and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, themſelves in the mean time fiſhed in thoſe troubled Waters.</hi> Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephus <hi>frequently bewails them as the great Plague of the Nation. He tells us that they ſcrupled not to kill many of the Nobility under pretence of their holding correſpondence with the</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib. 4.</hi> De bell. Judaico.</note> 
                  <hi>and betraying the liberty of their Country, boaſting that thereby they were the Benefactors and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours of the People: Joyning themſelves
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105495:13"/>
with the</hi> Idumeans, <hi>they ſlew the High-Prieſt, profaned the moſt Holy Places, and committed all manner of outrages, yet ſtiled themſelves the</hi> Zealots <hi>(pretending greateſt Zeal for the Glory of God.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor has this Phanatick Zeal, this kind of <hi>Zealots,</hi> been wanting, wherever Schiſm has prevailed in the after Ages of the World. The <hi>Donatiſts</hi> had among them an Order of men called <hi>Circumcelliones,</hi> that were wholly deſigned and ſet apart for theſe Zealotick exploits; they were as ſo many Hectors to fight for the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> on all occaſions, and were exactly among the <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts,</hi> as the <hi>Pſeudo-Zealots</hi> were among the <hi>Phariſees.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ep.</hi> 48.166.</note> 
                  <hi>Quas caedes,</hi> &amp;c. (<hi>ſaies St.</hi> Auguſtine) what Slaughters and Outrages did they not commit, when <hi>Julian</hi> reſtored the Churches to them, and gave them Power? and all this by belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, that they were inſpired by God to do ſuch extraordinary things, which they were ready to attempt,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105495:13"/>
whenever their Brethren, or their own Luſt did prompt them to it; the <hi>Donatiſt</hi> Biſhops inſtructing them ſoundly in this, That they did certainly dye Martyrs, who ſuffer'd Death for Religion ſake, as they called their Rebellious and moſt Murderous undertakings. Nor hath this Zealotick temper been more diſcernable in any than in the Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks of this latter Age. At the firſt planting of Presbytery in <hi>Scotland;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hiſtory of the Reformation of the Church of <hi>Scotland, p. 387.</hi>
                  </note> in Mr. <hi>Knox</hi>'s Diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with Ld. Secretary <hi>Lethington,</hi> about the Power of Princes, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> being asked whether the Subjects ought to ſuppreſs the Queen, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing her an Idolater <hi>[or Papiſt]?</hi> Mr. <hi>Knox</hi>'s Anſwer was, <hi>That not only Idolatry ought to be ſuppreſſed, but the Idolater alſo ought to die: But by whom</hi> (ſaid the Secretary <hi>Lethington?) by the People of God, ſaid Mr.</hi> Knox; <hi>for the command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was to</hi> Iſrael (ſaies he) <hi>Hear O</hi> Iſrael, <hi>the Statutes and the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of the Lord thy God; yet,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105495:14"/>
commandment is given, That if Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry be committed in any City, the whole body of the People riſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the City, ſparing neither Man, Woman, nor Child.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secretary. <hi>But there's no command given to deſtroy their King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Knox. <hi>If he be an Idolater, (or Papiſt) I find no Priviledg</hi> [or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption] <hi>given to him more than to the People, to offend Gods Majeſty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secretary. <hi>I grant that; but Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may not be Judges to their King, to puniſh him, tho he be an Idolater.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Knox. <hi>God is the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Judg to him, as well as to the People; ſo that what his word commands to be puniſhed in one, is not to be abſolved in the other — and that the People; yea, or a part of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may not execute Gods Judgments againſt their King being an Offender, you have no other warrant for, than your own Imagination.</hi> Whereupon the Lord Secretary <hi>Lethington,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for his Papers, produced the Authority of <hi>Luthor, Melancthon,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105495:14"/>
Muſculus,</hi> and <hi>Bucer,</hi> for the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Non-reſiſtance in any caſe: And in another place,<note place="margin">Hiſtory of the Reformation of the Church of <hi>Scotland, p. 393.</hi>
                  </note> Mr. <hi>Knox</hi> ſaies, <hi>That God has armed Subjects againſt their natural King, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to take Vengeance on him, according to Divine Law; and that accordingly Gods people have executed Gods Law againſt their King, having no further regard to him in that behalf, than if he had been the most ſimple Subject in the Realm.</hi> And in a Sermon before a great part of the Nobility. <hi>Ask of the Queen</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>that which by Gods word you may juſtly require;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Page 358.</note> 
                  <hi>and if ſhe will not agree with you in God, you are not bound to agree with her in the Devil.</hi> And when the Queen asked him, Whether he allowed that her Subjects ſhould take her Sword into their hand? His Anſwer was—<hi>They ſin not that bridle Kings when they Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs.</hi> For which he inſtances in <hi>Elias</hi>'s not ſparing <hi>Jezabel</hi>'s falſe Prophets, and <hi>Baal</hi>'s Prieſts, tho
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105495:15"/>
King <hi>Ahab</hi> ſtood by. And <hi>Samuel</hi>'s not ſparing to ſlay <hi>Agag</hi> King of <hi>Amalek,</hi> and <hi>Phineas</hi>'s killing <hi>Zim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri</hi> and <hi>Cosbi,</hi> tho no Magiſtrate; and in the People's conſpiring againſt <hi>Amaziah</hi> King of <hi>Judah;</hi> their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing him to <hi>Lachiſh,</hi> and killing him. And ſo throughout all Ages, among Hereticks and Schiſmaticks, and none elſe, there have always been ſuch rebellious <hi>Pſeudo Zealots,</hi> acting quite contrary to the Goſpel-Religion, and to the Precepts of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and to the practice of all the Catholick Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, and Orthodox Chriſtians of the Primitive time, and all in imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of thoſe Jewiſh Worthies, <hi>Samuel, Elias, Phineas,</hi> &amp;c. who living under a perfect <hi>Theocraſie,</hi> had that real and miraculous im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe of Gods Spirit, and that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Guidance and Commiſſion from Heaven, which the moſt fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent and daring <hi>Zealot</hi> in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian World never could <hi>[without rank Phanaticiſm]</hi> ſo much as pretend to.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:105495:15"/>And as their Principle, ſo their Practice: At the firſt ſtarting of <hi>Presbytery</hi> in <hi>Geneva, Anno</hi> 1535. When the Biſhop of <hi>Geneva</hi> would not admit of the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations, <hi>Viret</hi> and <hi>Farellus</hi> with their Followers, preſently turned <hi>Zealots,</hi> drove the Biſhop out of Town, and ſet up <hi>Calvin</hi> in his ſtead, diſclaiming all Allegiance to their Duke and Biſhop. From <hi>Geneva</hi> the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Diſcipline was ſent into <hi>France,</hi> where the Abettors of them [called <hi>Albigenſes</hi>] propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it at firſt, by their Arch-Zealot the Earl of <hi>Tholouſe</hi>'s mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering <hi>Trincannel</hi> the Viſcount, and chief Governour of the City <hi>Bezi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> and daſhing out the Biſhops teeth. In the Low Countries, <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery</hi> was firſt ſet up at <hi>Embden</hi> in <hi>Friezeland,</hi> by renouncing all Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to their Prince, and taking up Arms againſt him, and ſetting themſelves in form of a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. In <hi>Scotland,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Bothwell</hi> and his Accomplices, roſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105495:16"/>
Forces to Depoſe and Murder the King, under pretence of removing the Popiſh Lords, and promoting the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Diſcipline. The <hi>Gowries</hi> Conſpiracy to kill King <hi>James,</hi> was ſo approved of by the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Miniſters of <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> that they refuſed to give thanks for the Kings Deliverance, tho com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Kings Proclamation ſo to do. And as the <hi>Circumcillian-Zealots</hi> (of whom hereafter) were taught theſe practices by their <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt</hi> Biſhops and Miniſters, ſo were theſe <hi>Presbyterian Zealots</hi> by their Miniſters, as may be ſeen in the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of <hi>Knox, Buchanan, Willock,</hi> the <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Theſ.</hi> 358, 368, 147, 136, 151, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> Holy Commonwealth: Of all which the Murder of King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, the late Murder of the Archbiſhop of St. <hi>Andrews,</hi> and the late Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy of 83. againſt King <hi>Charles</hi> the ſecond, are all moſt barbarous and bloody Comments. In ſhort that the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Sectaries, now called <hi>Diſſenting Proteſtants,</hi> are perfect Zealots, Enthuſiaſtick Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105495:16"/>
is evident from hence, That ever ſince the Reformation from Popery, there has not been in any Proteſtant Countrey, any Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Maſſacre, Tumult, Treaſon, or Murders conſiderable, but what Papiſts or Phanatick, or both, had a hand in, as a means of Propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their Religion, on the ſame grounds and principles as all former Zealots did.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>GNOSTICKS.</head>
               <p>THeſe were the firſt and worſe Schiſmaticks, firſt and worſt Rebels in the Chriſtian Church.<note n="*" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Cave</hi> on the Life of St. <hi>Paul.</hi>
                  </note> The firſt Founder of them was <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus,</hi> who not being able to attain his ends of the Apoſtles in getting power to confer miraculous gifts, reſolved in diſcontent and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, to make Schiſms in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church: So that as the firſt Schiſmatick in the World was a Devil, ſo the firſt Schiſmatick in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:105495:17"/>
the Chriſtian World was a Witch. He began his Schiſmatizing firſt at <hi>Samaria,</hi> the firſt place that embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the Chriſtian Faith.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> Hammon. <hi>Annot.</hi> Acts 8.12, 14.</note> Tho their Schiſms and Errors were broached in the Apoſtles times, yet they had not the name of <hi>Gnoſticks</hi> till after, when they aſſumed it to themſelves on pretence of greateſt Knowledg above other men, and particularly in myſtical Interpretations. They pretended to be well acquainted with the Holy Scriptures, to know all the Myſteries of the <hi>Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which pretended knowledg is that (ſaies Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi>) which the Apoſtle charges <hi>Timothy</hi> to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Annot. on</hi> 2 Pet. 1.5.</note> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.20. calling it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> knowledg falſly ſo called, from whence they called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Gnoſticks, i. e.</hi> knowing Perſons, or the knowing Party: And by a ſtrange Liberty, which they took in Interpreting the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, brought in (as the Apoſtle calls them) <hi>damnable Doctrines,</hi> ſuch as reſiſting Magiſtrates, Liberty
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105495:17"/>
in the exerciſe of Uncleanneſs; for which they were called <hi>Borboritae,</hi> whereby they greatly ſtrengthened their Faction.</p>
               <p>And as they pretended to greater Knowledg, ſo to greater Piety and Holineſs than others, (as <note n="*" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Ham.</hi> Annot. <hi>1</hi> Joh. <hi>1.10.</hi> Let. H.</note> 
                  <hi>Irenaeus</hi> ſaies) they called themſelves the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual; this is the Character of the <hi>Gnoſticks</hi> (ſaies he) to live in all Carnality and Uncharitableneſs, and yet pretend themſelves to be the moſt perfect men. But the greateſt pretenſion was, that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Liberty which the Goſpel in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtated them in, and on theſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts they ſeparated themſelves, oppoſed the Apoſtles and Governors of the Church, depoſed the Orthodox Chriſtians, as Carnal, and not having the Spirit; and looking on all others (beſide their own Party) as Ignorant, they pretended to know more than the Biſhops (ſaith <note n="‖" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Ham.</hi> Annot. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to <hi>2d</hi> Ep. of <hi>John.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Ignatius.</hi>) Yea, than the Apoſtles themſelves, ſaies <hi>Epiphanius.</hi> Againſt theſe <hi>Gnoſtick-Sectaries,</hi> St. <hi>Peter,</hi> St. <hi>Paul,</hi> St. <hi>James,</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:105495:18"/>
and St. <hi>John,</hi> direct their Epiſtles chiefly; and St. <hi>Jude</hi> his Epiſtle whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, where in leſs then ſix verſes he gives more than ſixteen diſtinctive marks whereby they may be known.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> on the place.</note>1. The firſt is their inſolence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Government, ver. 8. <hi>They deſpiſe Dominion, and ſpeak evil of Dignities,</hi> i.e. were ſawcy with the Government; of Antimagiſtratical and Tumultuous Carriage to'ards Governours; for which cauſe the Apoſtles preſs no one Doctrine in all their Epiſtles more than Loyalty and Obedience, not only to the good and gentle, but to the froward and wicked; not to good Governors as good, but to Governors as Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, and the Ordinance of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A ſecond mark the Apoſtle gives of the <hi>Gnoſtick-Sectaries,</hi> is their diſcontent and murmuring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Governors,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> on the place.</note> ver. 16. <hi>They are Murmurers, Complainers,</hi> never content with any Government. <hi>The Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, imports a ſecret muttering and grumbling; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:105495:18"/>
from</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Grunnio, <hi>to grunt like a Swine, importing a ſpeaking againſt another ſecretly with hatred and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience.</hi> Like ſome now-adays, who, if for committing a ſpoil in Gods Harveſt, Juſtice takes them by the Ears, with hideous outcrys they call all the compaſſionate Herd to condole their ſuffering, and that they call Perſecution, and the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering days of the Saints. Are any of them cut off by the hand of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice for their Seditious Villanies; How doth their Party murmur a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Magiſtrate, that they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer wrongfully? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As the Rebels <hi>Korah</hi> and his company did againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> Numb. 16.41. <hi>Ye have killed the people of the Lord, the people of the Lord,</hi> when God had declared from Heaven moſt miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly, that they were Rebels, and that his Wrath was kindled againſt them on the account of their being ſo.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A third mark is Erratick Zeal, verſe 13. <hi>Wandering Stars,</hi> ſo called,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Manton</hi> on the place.</note> as for inconſtancy and unſetledneſs,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105495:19"/>
pretending to be Stars and great lights, that a reindeed but falſe lights, and wandering Stars that ſeduce and miſlead into error; ſo wandering Stars for the irregularity of their motion; they ſeparate themſelves on the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of greateſt purity, yet allow themſelves in greateſt Impieties; like thoſe who have a Conſcience ſo tender, as to boggle at a Ceremony, and yet ſo tough as to bear a Schiſm, and make light of the great Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Goſpel, that great eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential of true Religion, Subjection for Conſcience ſake.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> Manton.</note>4. Their tumultuous Turbulence, verſe 13. <hi>raging waves of the Sea;</hi> ſo called for their boyſterous Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence (ſaies Dr. <hi>Manton</hi>) in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging mens minds againſt all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Rule in Church and State; putting all Places into Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion and Combuſtion, by Schiſm and Sedition. Whenever the Winds of Power,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Jenkins</hi> on the place.</note> Eccleſiaſtical or Civil, Word or Sword, blow againſt the Tide of their Factious Errors, they
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:105495:19"/>
preſently grow boiſterous, like raging Waves of the Sea.</p>
               <p n="5">5. A fifth mark the Apoſtle gives of the <hi>Gnoſtick Sectary,</hi> is their proud ſcorn and contempt of others, for which they are called <hi>mockers, verſe</hi> 18. They having incircled their heads with their own Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtick rays, and having ſwoln their imaginations into a ſelf-conceit of their greater Spirituality, and more Knowledg than others, did hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſeparate themſelves, and deſpiſe the true Church, and all ſober Members of it, as a People of low form, and unacquainted with the Heighths and Spiritualities of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p n="6">6. A ſixth Character St. <hi>Jude</hi> gives the <hi>Gnoſtick-Sectary,</hi> is their ſpecious pretences, and ſhew of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Knowledg above others, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtand their emptineſs of it: For which they are called <hi>Clouds with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out water, verſe</hi> 12. with the ſpecious Title of the ſpiritual and knowing People, the only true Church and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105495:20"/>
People of God, they reconciled Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, and all Licentiouſneſs; were Religious without Religion, Godly without Goodneſs, Chriſtians without Chriſtianity, <hi>Clouds with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Water.</hi> Clouds which tho ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with a counterfeit Light, which nothing exceeds but the Sun that lent it; yet when turned black, and grown numerous, diſcharge themſelves of moſt dangerous and terrible Principles of Thunder and Lightning, Storms and Tempeſts on the places of Religion, the High-Towers of Government, and whatever is great and eminent.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Another Character St. <hi>Jude</hi> gives of theſe Separatiſts of his time, is their ſucceſſeſneſs in proje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting againſt Governors and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, v. 11. <hi>They periſhed in the gainſaying of Korah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. Their Ignorant malice, ver. 10. <hi>They ſpeak evil of things they know not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. Obſtinate in their perſwaſion, v. 16. <hi>Walking after their own luſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:105495:20"/>10. Canting and Myſteriouſneſs of Phraſes, <hi>ver.</hi> 16. Their mouth ſpeaks great ſwelling words. With as many more diſtinctive Characters which the Apoſtle <hi>Jude</hi> gives in that one Chapter, whereby to know the <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> the Schiſmaticks of his time, who admired themſelves, and withdrew from the Communian of the beſt Chriſtians, under pretence of greater knowledg and holineſs than others.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>NOVATIANS.</head>
               <p>THis Sect commenced when <hi>Decius</hi> was Emperor,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Danaeus</hi>'s com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on St. <hi>Aug.</hi> de <hi>Haereſ.</hi> cap. <hi>38.</hi>
                  </note> and <hi>Cornelius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> in the year of Chriſt 220, which was 78 years before that of the <hi>Donatiſts.</hi> They had the Denomination from <hi>Nova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> the firſt Author of the Sect, who was a Presbyter of St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Carthage,</hi> and afterwards by
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:105495:21"/>
                  <hi>Cornelius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> was made a Presbyter of the Church. But (ſaies <hi>Danaeus</hi> on St. <hi>Auguſtine) Ad Epiſcopatum aſpirans, dolore repulſae,</hi> &amp;c. Aſpiring at the Biſhoprick of <hi>Rome, i. e.</hi> endeavouring to thruſt <hi>Cornelius</hi> out (for holding Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion (as they falſly accuſed him) with <hi>Trophimus</hi> one of the <hi>Thuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficati</hi>) and to make himſelf Biſhop in his ſtead, was ſadly diſappointed in the attempt; whereupon in grief and diſcontent at the diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he joyns himſelf with <hi>Nova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tianus,</hi> once his Scholar, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward his Fellow Presbyter, who having drawn many after them, <hi>Seceſſionem ab Orthodoxis fecerant, &amp; ſeorſim ſuas Eccleſias &amp; Baſilicas habebant:</hi> Refuſed Communion with the Orthodox, and met in their Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilicae, which St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly calls Conventicles. They made the Separation on the occaſion of the Orthodox Biſhops receiving lapſed Penitents into Communion; in oppoſition to which <hi>Novatus</hi> and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:105495:21"/>
his Adherents taught, that the Church of God was to conſiſt of none but Saints; and therefore, if through infirmity, or the rage of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, any lapſed into Idolatry, or the like groſs Sin after Baptiſm, they would never receive them more into Communion with them, but gave them up as damned Perſons, and ſuch as were never capable of Repentance, notwithſtanding the greateſt and moſt infallible ſigns of true repentance that could be ſhewn. Upon this moſt ſtrict and rigid, moſt cenſorious and uncharitable Opinion, they ſeparated from the Orthodox Chriſtians, becauſe they received the Penitents into Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, upon ſufficient Evidence of their Repentance given. And this was ſoon improved into ſuch a Schiſm, that laſted from the Reign of <hi>Decius,</hi> to the Reign of <hi>Archadius,</hi> which was a 148 years, and much longer. All that while diſturbing the Peace of Church and State, to the great prejudice of Chriſtianity,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:105495:22"/>
in moſt places of the World, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially <hi>Italy.</hi> Theſe Sectaries were alſo called <hi>Cathari,</hi> i. e. <hi>Puritans,</hi> a name not given them by others, but arrogated to themſelves (ſaith St. <hi>Auguſtine) Se ipſos iſto nomine quaſi propter munditiem ſuperbiſſime,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. de <hi>Haereſ.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp; odioſiſſimè nominant.</hi> They were ſo called (ſays his Commentator) becauſe they ſeparated from the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox, as more Pure and Holy, as the only true Church and People of God; accounting all the Church-Aſſemblies of the Orthodox Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians polluted with the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the lapſed Penitents; on which very account <hi>Danaeus</hi> calls them <hi>Fanaticks.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Comment on <hi>Aug.</hi> de <hi>Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ.</hi> c. <hi>38.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Haecuna ratio vel maxime Fanaticos iſtos impulit, ut ſe</hi> Catharos <hi>appellarent.</hi> And on which very account the Orthodox Chriſtians were called <hi>Catholicks,</hi> in oppoſition to that uncharitable Opinion of the <hi>Novatians, Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts,</hi> and other Sectaries of old (as the Papiſts do of late) in confining the only true Church and People of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:105495:22"/>
God to their own party. Theſe <hi>Novatians</hi> or <hi>Kathari</hi> looked upon the poor Orthodox Penitents, as ſo many Reprobates, calling them in ſcorn <hi>Thurificati;</hi> but themſelves and their party <hi>Purificati;</hi> and as <hi>Danaus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Sub ſpecioſo illo</hi> Purificato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, <hi>&amp; ſanctorum nomine &amp; fuco, turpiſſima tum in Doctrina, tum in vita ſcelera tegebant.</hi> That under the ſpecious name and diſguiſe of the <hi>Purificati,</hi> and the Saints, they did cloak the baſeſt Villanies, both in Life and Doctrine. By Doctrine meaning chiefly that of their bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous rigor to'ards the lapſed Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitents. For they were at firſt for the moſt part ſound in the Faith. As St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaid of the <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, De ſola communione infaeliciter litigârunt.</hi> They ſeparated on the account of not receiving lapſed Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitents into Church-Communion, on the account of their conceited purity above all others; which is that <hi>Danaeus</hi> calls, <hi>Pernicioſiſſimum illud dogma quod in eccleſiae exitium
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:105495:23"/>
cudit</hi> Novatus.<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> A moſt pernicious Principle framed by <hi>Novatus,</hi> on purpoſe to deſtroy the Church; which Principle prevailed very much (<hi>floruit</hi> ſaies <hi>Danaeus</hi>) in <hi>Arcadius</hi>'s Reign, which was 148 years after it's firſt broaching, and was at laſt exploded by the Preaching and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputing of St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople, Cyril</hi> Biſhop of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandria,</hi> and <hi>Innocent</hi> the firſt Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> but eſpecially St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Carthage.</hi> As alſo by the ſevere Proceedings of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Biſhops againſt them, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly in the Council held at <hi>Rome,</hi> in which were 60 Biſhops beſides Presbyters; where they were by the common Vote of the Church exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Communion of the Church,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Cave</hi> Life of St. <hi>Cyprian.</hi>
                  </note> not ſo much on the account of their different Sentiments about pardon of Sin, and Eccleſiaſtical Penance, as their inſolent and domineering Temper, their proud and ſurly Carriage, their rigorous and impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Impoſing their way upon
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:105495:23"/>
other Churches, their bold denying the Governors of the Church that great power lodged in them, and particularly in remitting Crimes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Repentance; which ſeems to have been the very Soul and Spirit of <hi>Novatianiſm.</hi> The Schiſm was alſo vehemently oppoſed by <hi>Dionyſius Alexandrinus,</hi> of which there is par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular inſtance in his Pathetical Epiſtle to <hi>Novatus,</hi> which in regard of its brevity, it may not be grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous here to ſubjoin.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Dionyſius</hi> to <hi>Novatus</hi> our Brother, greeting.</head>
                     <p>For as much as you your ſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, you were unwillingly drawn into this Schiſm, make it appear ſo by your willing and ready return into the Church; for better it were to ſuffer any thing, than that the Church of God ſhould be rent aſſunder: Nor is it leſs glorious to ſuffer Martyrdom on this account, than in the caſe of not ſacrificing to Idols; yea, in my
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:105495:24"/>
wind much more honourable: For in the one caſe, a man ſuffers only for his own Soul; but in this he undergoes Martyrdom for the whole Church of God; and if now thou ſhalt perſwade and reduce thy Brethren to Peace and Concord, thy merit will outweigh thy Crime: The one will not be charged to thy reproach, and the other will be mentioned to thy praiſe; and ſuppoſe thou ſhalt not be able to perſuade them; yet however ſave thy own Soul: I pray that thou mayeſt live peaceably, and farewell in the Lord. <hi>Dionyſ.</hi> Ep. p. <hi>247.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>MELETIANS.</head>
               <p>THE <hi>Meletian</hi> Schiſm began a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the year 286, when <hi>Conſtantine</hi> was Emperor, and <hi>Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſter</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome:</hi> The <hi>Mele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> were for the moſt part the ſame with the <hi>Novatians;</hi> the whole
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:105495:24"/>
difference between them, lies in theſe three particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Novatians</hi> denied to the lapſed any poſſibility of Repentance;<note place="margin">Danaeus <hi>on St.</hi> Aug. <hi>de</hi> Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ. <hi>cap.</hi> 48.</note> theſe allowed them a poſſibility of Repentance, but agreed with the <hi>Novatians</hi> in denying them Church-Communion, notwithſtanding the moſt infallible marks of true Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance that could be given.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They differed in time, as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus, Hi plane ſimiles ſunt</hi> Novati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anis, <hi>a quibus ſunt profecti, ſed tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore poſteriores:</hi> This Schiſm not commencing till 66 years after the <hi>Novatian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. They differ'd in their Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, or firſt Authors; their Origine, or firſt riſe. As the <hi>Novatian</hi> Schiſm was firſt made, and promoted by <hi>Novatus,</hi> ſo was the <hi>Meletian</hi> Schiſm by <hi>Meletius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lycus</hi> in <hi>Thebais</hi> in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> a Perſon of greateſt Authority and Power. And next to <hi>Peter</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> was Director General of all the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:105495:25"/>
Affairs of the Church. The Schiſm aroſe in this manner: The ſeverity of the <hi>Diocleſian</hi> Perſecution tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed many of all orders of men to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the Faith,<note place="margin">Epiph. <hi>adv.</hi> Haereſ. Melet. 68. <hi>p.</hi> 306. <hi>ap D.</hi> Cave <hi>Life of</hi> Athan.</note> and comply with the Gentile rites; who afterwards repenting of what they had done, applied themſelves to the Martyrs and Confeſſors in priſon for Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, that they may be reſtored to peace and Communion with the Church. This <hi>Meletius</hi> and others would by no means yield to. <hi>Peter</hi> acted with the Reſentments and Compaſſion of a common Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, was for the more mild opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, That a time of penance being aſſigned, they might be re-admitted into the Church. But not being able to prevail, he hung up his Mantle croſs the priſon, crying out, They that are on my ſide, let them come hither; they that are for <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letius</hi> let them go to him; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſome Biſhops came over to him, the reſt remained with <hi>Mele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> which widened the difference
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:105495:25"/>
into ſuch a breach, that ever after they kept their ſeparate Aſſemblies, refuſing to communicate with the Orthodox Biſhops. But it was not long before <hi>Meletus</hi> himſelf ſtood in need of that Mercy which he had ſo uncharitably denied to others, being through the infirmity of his Faith betrayed to ſacrifice to Idols:<note place="margin">Socr. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 6.</note> For which, as alſo for his Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical proceedings, he was deprived of his Biſhoprick by <hi>Peter,</hi> in a common meeting of Biſhops. <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letius</hi> having got out of Priſon, ſtill bore up himſelf with the Reputation of a Biſhop, gathering Churches of his own Party, ordaining Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Deacons to his Schiſmatical Aſſemblies, and refuſing to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate with the Orthodox Churches, on pretence of greater Zeal for the Glory of God,<note place="margin">Commen. c. <hi>48.</hi>
                  </note> and ſtricter Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline to'awds the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius</hi> calls the lapſed: By which ſpecious pretences, this Schiſm which <hi>Danaeus</hi> calls Poyſon, had infected moſt parts of the Chriſtian World,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:105495:26"/>
and was a laſting Plague,<note place="margin">Latiſſimì ſparſum èſt, &amp; a Monarchis pretextu ſeverio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris in <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> diſciplinae, &amp; Zeli in Deum majoris: Epba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, adeo ut omnes pene Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiani nominis regiones labife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerit; Diutiſſime etiam duravit venenum hoc in <hi>Aegypto,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Arianis Haereticis</hi> ſeſe <hi>Meleti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ani</hi> adjunxerunt, &amp;c. <hi>Dan.</hi> on St. <hi>Aug.</hi> de <hi>Haereſ.</hi> c. <hi>48.</hi>
                  </note> and of very long continuance in the Chriſtian Church. They ſtiled themſelves <hi>the Church of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs:</hi> Tho <hi>Meletius</hi> himſelf died a Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick and Apoſtate, when <hi>Peter</hi> the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Biſhop, that oppoſed him, received the Crown of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom, <hi>Athan. Apol.</hi> 11. As <hi>Arrius</hi> himſelf was at firſt a <hi>Meletian,</hi> ſo the <hi>Meletians</hi> were at laſt <hi>Arrians.</hi> As, Schiſm generally uſeth to ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate in Hereſie. They were at firſt ſound in the Faith, <hi>Primum cum Orthodoxis in Doctrina fidei plane conſentiebant,</hi> ſaith <hi>Danaeus;</hi> and when they differed from the Orthodox in nothing but Church-Communion; even then did they join with the <hi>Arrians</hi> againſt the Orthodox Biſhops, Petitioning the <hi>Emperor</hi> againſt them, and ſlander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them in moſt Diabolical man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:105495:26"/>
                  <hi>Athanaſius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi> whom<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Orat.</hi> 21. <hi>p.</hi> 378.</note> 
                  <hi>Nazianzen</hi> after great commendation of his incomparable Learning, and ſtrict Piety, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Watchings and Faſtings, Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Praiſes, calls <hi>A Comforter to the Miſerable, a Staff to the Aged, a Tutor to the Youth, a Benefactor to the Poor, a Steward to the Rich, a Patron to the Widows, a Father to the Orphans, a Harbour to the Stranger, a Phyſician to the Sick, a man of ſuch Apoſtolick ſanctity, and Angelick Diſpoſition, that his Doctrine was accounted the Rule of Orthodoxy, and his Life the very Standard of the Epiſcopal Function: He was</hi> (ſaies that <hi>Encomiaſt) the moſt holy Eye and Light of the World, a Pillar of the Faith, and a ſecond</hi> John <hi>the Baptiſt;</hi> yet did theſe <hi>Meletian</hi> Schiſmaticks (when they were otherwiſe ſound in the Faith) join with the <hi>Arrian</hi> Hereticks in loading this holy man with falſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations, and hell-bred Slanders, calling him <hi>Sathanius;</hi> accuſing him
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:105495:27"/>
as <hi>Arſenius Euplus, Pachomius,</hi> and others of the <hi>Meletian</hi> Schiſm did, of Murder,<note place="margin">Dan. <hi>on</hi> Aug. <hi>de</hi> Haereſ. <hi>c.</hi> 48.</note> and the like helliſh Crimes, as in the Council of <hi>Tyre,</hi> and other places; till at laſt by that black art of Slandering, they prevailed with the Emperor to baniſh him. Of the notoriouſneſs of their Slandering, there is among many others, which a late Writer gives from <hi>Sozomen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Cave</hi> the Life of <hi>Athan.</hi> Sect. <hi>5.</hi> n. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Theodoret,</hi> and <hi>Ruffinus,</hi> this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. The <hi>Meletian</hi> Biſhops in the Synod of <hi>Tyre,</hi> accuſed <hi>Athanaſius</hi> of raviſhing a Woman, whom they had prevailed with to come into the Council, and to own and atteſt the Fact; who accordingly declared, that <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in her own Houſe, violently forced her into lewd Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> came into the Court, attended with <hi>Timotheus</hi> one of his Presbyters, who was by agreement with <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> to take his part upon him. The Judg cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling upon <hi>Athanaſius</hi> to Anſwer to the matter of Fact, he ſtood ſilent. But <hi>Timotheus</hi> turning to the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:105495:27"/>
                  <hi>Woman</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>was I ever in your houſe? did I ever, as you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, offer violence to you?</hi> Yes, yes, ſaies the Woman, you are the man that forcibly preſſed upon me, and ſtained my Chaſtity and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. The cheat thus plainly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering it ſelf, put the Contrivers of it to the bluſh; but no end to their falſe Accuſations. They pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to accuſe him of Oppreſſion, Murder, and <hi>[like the modern cry of popiſhly affected]</hi> of compliance with the <hi>Thurificati,</hi> till at laſt he was deprived of his Biſhoprick, and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed.<note place="margin">Ibid. <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. <hi>n.</hi> 6.</note> The like they did to <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtathius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Antioch,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Catholicks that oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them, and endeavoured the Unity of the Church. And tho the <hi>Arrian</hi> Hereticks joyned with the <hi>Meletian</hi> Schiſmaticks in theſe Diabolical practices againſt the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Chriſtians, yet were theſe principal in it. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t</hi> Meletiani (ſaies <hi>Danaeus) pene Soli divinum illum,</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſium <hi>conarentur opprimere,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:105495:28"/>In the firſt General Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> in which were 318 <hi>Biſhops,</hi> beſides innumerable <hi>Presbyters, Deacons,</hi> and <hi>Acoluthi;</hi> an Aſſembly of men ſo venerable for their Age, their confeſſions, and conſtancy in the Faith, for the Gravity of their Manners, the Wiſdom, Learning, and Reaſon of their Arguments and Diſcourſes, and meeting out of all parts of the Chriſtian World; was certainly the moſt Auguſt and Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Aſſembly that ever the World ſaw, either before or ſince. In this Council the <hi>Arrian</hi> Hereſie being condemned, they proceeded to take into conſideration the <hi>Meletian</hi> Schiſm;<note place="margin">Ep. Synod <hi>Nice</hi> ap <hi>Socr.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi> ap Dr. <hi>Cave</hi> the Life of <hi>Athan.</hi>
                  </note> they deprived <hi>Meletius</hi> of all his Epiſcopal Juriſdiction and Power, leſt he ſhould excite the ſame Troubles and Factions which he had formerly raiſed in the Church of God. And tho the <hi>Meletians</hi> were at that time ſound in the Faith, yet on no other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count then the Separation did this venerable Council declare in their
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:105495:28"/>
Letter to the Church of <hi>Alexandria, That in ſtrict Juſtice they deſerved no Pity.</hi> The Council of <hi>Sardica</hi> did the like. Having depoſed <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> a <hi>Meletian</hi> Biſhop, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed in that Council, <hi>That all Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination made by him, ſhould be null and void;</hi> which is in effect to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, that a Schiſmatick is <hi>ipſo facto</hi> diveſted of his Miniſterial Function, and no true Miniſter on the account of his Schiſm.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>DONATISTS.</head>
               <p>THE light of the Goſpel had ſcarce been well fix'd and diffuſed in the World, but the Devil ſtired up the Pagan Emperors of <hi>Rome</hi> to extinguiſh it, by perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting the Profeſſors of it, with the moſt grievous Torments and Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that the moſt twiſted Malice and Subtilty of Earth and Hell
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:105495:29"/>
could deviſe; and that in ſuch mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, that in the <hi>Diocleſian</hi> Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, which laſted for ten years, there were put to Death Seventeen thouſand in a Month. And of the <hi>Decian</hi> Perſecution, <hi>Nicephorus</hi> ſaies, <hi>It was as eaſie to number the Sands of the Sea, as to reckon up all that ſuffer'd Martyrdom in that one Perſcution under</hi> Decius. This bloody work continued with its little Intermiſſions for about 250 years <hi>(viz.)</hi> from the Reign of <hi>Nero, Anno Dom.</hi> 54. to the Reign of <hi>Conſtantius Clorus, Anno Dom.</hi> 304. Theſe Flames of Perſecution were ſcarcely extinguiſhed, and peace and quiet reſtored to the Church, but new Heats and Lights were raiſed by the pride and diſcontent of Schiſmaticks, which infeſted the Church of God, till <hi>Mahometaniſm</hi> and <hi>Popery</hi> divided the greateſt part of the World, and were more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious to Chriſtiany, than all the ten Perſecutions. Among theſe Schiſmaticks, the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> were
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:105495:29"/>
chief; who were (as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſhews at large) ſound in the Faith; but as<note n="‖" place="margin">Ep. <hi>50.</hi> let. O. P.</note> he ſaies, <hi>De ſola communio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae infaeliciter litigarunt, &amp; contra unitatem Chriſti rebelles inimicitias perverſitate ſui erroris exercuerunt.</hi> They quarrelled only about Church-Communion [<hi>as the</hi> Novatians <hi>and</hi> Meletians <hi>in another part of the World did</hi>] and through the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſneſs of their Error, exerciſed (ſaies he) Rebellious enmity againſt the Unity of the Church.</p>
               <p>For the right underſtanding of the riſe and progreſs of this Schiſm, we muſt note, that <hi>Diocleſian</hi> in the heat and heighth of his Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, had put forth an Edict that Chriſtians ſhould deliver up their Bibles, and the Writings of the Church, to be burnt; which Edict was proſecuted with ſo much rage and vigor, that many Chriſtians to avoid the Storm, deliver'd up their Bibles, to the great Scorn of their Enemies, for which they were called <hi>Traditores.</hi> The Perſecution being
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:105495:30"/>
over, ſome of the Orthodox refuſed to receive them into Communion, notwithſtanding the greateſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that could be given of their true Repentance; the difference broke out into open Schiſm and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and gave Birth to that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Sect of the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> in the year 298, which was about twelve years after the <hi>Meletian</hi> Schiſm was made, when <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great was Emperor, and <hi>Silveſter</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> in this wiſe:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Botrus</hi> and <hi>Celeſius,</hi> two Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, being in Competition with <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilian,</hi> for the Biſhoprick of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage; Cecilian,</hi> a man of note for Learning and Integrity, was by the general Suffrage of that whole Church choſen Biſhop. <hi>Botrus</hi> and <hi>Celeſius</hi> diſcontented hereat,<note place="margin">Opt. <hi>p.</hi> 14. Danae <hi>on</hi> Aug. <hi>de</hi> Haereſ. <hi>c.</hi> 69.</note> with ſome others that had been proceeded againſt by <hi>Cecilian,</hi> refuſed to hold Communion with him, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly <hi>Lucilla</hi> a Spaniſh Lady, rich and factious, thinking her ſelf af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronted by <hi>Cecilian</hi>'s ſharp reproof
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:105495:30"/>
of her Superſtitious practice <hi>[in kiſſing the Reliques of ſome Martyr, before her receiving the Sacrament]</hi> in Diſcontent and Anger joyns her ſelf to <hi>Botrus</hi> and <hi>Celecius,</hi> and by the help of her money, calls in <hi>Donatus à caſa nigra,</hi> with ſome others to ſtrengthen the Party: [<hi>much after the ſame manner as</hi> Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret <hi>and</hi> Farellus <hi>did</hi> Calvin <hi>at</hi> Geneva.] This <hi>Donatus</hi> was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently made the head of the Faction; who tho himſelf, and moſt of his Party had been <hi>Traditors</hi> [i.e. <hi>ſuch as to evade the</hi> Diocleſian <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, had delivered up their Bibles to be burnt</hi>] yet accuſes <hi>Cecilian</hi> of being a <hi>Traditor,</hi> and on that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count not fit to be Biſhop of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage;</hi> whereupon they ſet up <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jorinus</hi> a Presbyter and Mock-biſhop in the ſtead of <hi>[or rather againſt]</hi> the good Biſhop <hi>Cecilian;</hi> and thus the Schiſm began by erecting Altar againſt Altar,<note place="margin">Dan <hi>on</hi> Aug. <hi>de</hi> Haereſ <hi>c.</hi> 69.</note> in ſetting up <hi>Majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinus</hi> a Pſeudo-Biſhop againſt <hi>Ceci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi> the lawful and good Biſhop
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:105495:31"/>
of <hi>Carthage:</hi> But this <hi>Majorinus</hi> died immediately upon the firſt broach of the Schiſm, and was ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded by <hi>Donatus à caſis nigris,</hi> and he by <hi>Donatus Magnus,</hi> from whom they were called <hi>Donatiſts:</hi> priding themſelves much in this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination, <hi>è parte Donati:</hi> The Schiſm increaſed daily, and began by the Conduct of <hi>Donatus</hi> to ſet up private meetings,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> which they called the only True and Holy Church of God, but which St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> commonly calls Conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles; and after a ſhort time began to build for their Meetings, <hi>baſilicas non neceſſarias,</hi> as <hi>Optatus</hi> calls them: And this pernicious Schiſm being thus founded in proud and ambitious Diſcontent, it was propagated much after the ſame manner, and by the ſame means as well as all other Schiſms uſually are, as</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Pretenſions to greater purity and ſtricter piety than others:</hi> Thus they taught, The Church is to conſiſt of none but ſuch as be holy, and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:105495:31"/>
that ſuch were not to be found in the Church of <hi>Carthage,</hi> but in the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> ſeparate Congregations only; for which St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> frequently reproves them, and particularly in that one<note n="⸫" place="margin">Ep. <hi>48</hi> lett. &amp;c. lett. p.</note> Epiſtle to <hi>Vincentius,</hi> of boaſting of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as the only Perſons in whom the Son of Man ſhould find Faith when he came; and in the ſame Epiſtle, compares them to the <hi>Phariſees</hi> on this very account, For juſtifying themſelves, and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing others, which he calls an eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing of their own Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That which was at-firſt pretended by the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> as the ground of the Schiſm, was, that <hi>Cecilian</hi> the Orthodox Biſhop of <hi>Carthage,</hi> was a <hi>Traditor;</hi> that he and the other Catholick Biſhops had admitted lapſed Perſons into their Church-Communion, whereby all their Churches were defiled, and ought not to be communicated with, and therefore ſeparated from them, on
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:105495:32"/>
the account of greater purity:<note place="margin">Hiſt. of the <hi>Donat.</hi>
                  </note> In the Meeting which the Emperor <hi>Honorius</hi> appointed at the <hi>Gargilian</hi> Baths between the Catholicks and <hi>Donatiſts</hi> for the compoſing of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters between them, the <hi>Donatists</hi> refuſed ſo much as to ſit in their Company: <hi>Primilianus</hi> the <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tist</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Carthage,</hi> his Words were, <hi>Indignum eſt ut filii Martyrum eſt progenies Traditorum in unum co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eant; i. e.</hi> It is not fit that the Sons of Martyrs <hi>[as they called them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves]</hi> and the Sons of <hi>Traditors [as they called the Orthodox]</hi> ſhould ſit together; and another of them, <hi>Odi Eccleſiam malignantium &amp; cum impiis non ſedebo:</hi> I hate the Church of the <hi>Malignants [the very ſame Name that the Schiſmatick-Rebels of</hi> 43 <hi>called the Orthodox and Loyal Engliſh by</hi>]: Such were their great pretenſions to ſtrict Purity and holy Ordinances, that they waſhed the very Walls and Pavements of their Religious places where any of the Orthodox Chriſtians had been.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:105495:32"/>2. A ſecond Expedient that they uſed for the propagating of their Schiſm, was their proud and cenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſlandering and traducing the Orthodox: This <hi>Donatiſt</hi> Schiſm was firſt of all founded in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content that <hi>Donatus</hi> had took at his not being preferred to the <hi>Biſhoprick</hi> of <hi>Carthage</hi> before <hi>Cecilian,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he ſeparated and propagated the Schiſm very much by this very means,<note place="margin">Dan. <hi>on</hi> Aug. de Haereſ. <hi>cap.</hi> 69.</note> traducing <hi>Cecilian</hi> as a <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor,</hi> as no Miniſter of Chriſt, nor the people that adhered to him true members of the Chriſtian Church; that they had no true Sacraments, nor ſaving Ordinances; that all were corrupted by Idolatry and Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;<note place="margin">Opt. <hi>p.</hi> 47.</note> and thus they generally called the Catholicks, Pagans and Idolaters. But more particularly the venerable St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> having in publick Meetings ſoundly baffled <hi>Petilian, Creſconius,</hi> and others of their Ring-leaders, and many ways mauled their Schiſmatick Cauſe <hi>[for which he has been always ſtiled
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:105495:33"/>
Donatiſtarum mallaeus];</hi> him they traduced as a contentions Diſputer, a wrangling Sophiſter, and a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verter of Souls, rather to be avoided than diſputed with, and to be dealt with as a Wolf, or any beaſt of Prey; and accordingly they employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their <hi>Circumcellions</hi> to murder him, but that the Providence of God did ſo miraculouſly preſerve him, once by miſleading him out of his way, and at other times in miraculous manner; The Emperor they traduced as miſled by <hi>Hoſius</hi> the famous Biſhop of <hi>Corduba,</hi> by <hi>Stilicho</hi> the great Staes-man, and others whom they ſtiled Evil Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors;<note place="margin">Hiſt. of the <hi>Dona. 135.</hi>
                  </note> of <hi>Menſurius, Cecilians</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſor, they ſaid, he was <hi>Tyranno crudelior, &amp; carnifice ſevior;</hi> more raging than a Tyrant, and more cruel than a Hangman; againſt the Magiſtracy it ſelf (ſays <hi>Danaeus</hi>) they did <hi>[multa emovere, &amp; impie blatterare,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>C.</hi> 69.</note> 
                  <hi>tanquam eccleſiae lupi &amp; peſtes magiſtratus eſſent]</hi> lye mutter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and vomiting out wickedly, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:105495:33"/>
the Magiſtrates the very Wolfs and Plagues of the Church; and all this to promote the Schiſm, by keeping up prejudice in the minds of People, and to maintain in them an ill opinion of their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miniſters and Magiſtrates, who otherwiſe might have reduced them to Unity and Communion with the Orthodox Chriſtians.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Obſtinacy in their Perſwaſion; they had been ſo oft condemned in full Councils, and yet perſiſted in their error,<note place="margin">Ep. <hi>167.</hi> let. O.</note> that made St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in indignation ſay, <hi>Puto quod ſi ipſe diabolus autoritate judicis quem ultro elegerat toties vinceretur, non eſſet tam impudens ut in eâ perſiſteret:</hi> I think that if the Devil himſelf had been ſo oft condemned [as theſe Dotiſts have been by Judges of their own chuſing] he would not have been ſo impudent as to perſiſt in ſuch a Cauſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A fourth Expedient which they uſed in propagating the Schiſm, was Phanaticiſm, or Enthuſiaſm;
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:105495:34"/>
When <hi>Donatus</hi> had a mind to engage the <hi>Circumcellians</hi> in any barbarous Enterprize, his Cuſtom was, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend that an Angel had appear'd to him, and aſſured him of ſucceſs in anſwer to his Prayers, <hi>Oravit Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus &amp; reſpondit ei Deus</hi> (ſays <hi>Opta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi>); and of all the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> ſaith <hi>Danaeus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>C.</hi> 69.</note> 
                  <hi>Jactant Revelationes, &amp; Entheuſiaſmos ut ſua dogmata plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilius confirment, &amp; ſe ſanctos per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectoſque ſumoſius glorientur;</hi> to the end, they may make their Opinons in Religion the more plauſible, and may the more ſpeciouſly boaſt of themſelves as the Saints and perfect ones, they pretended Inſpiration and Revelation from God; that their Cauſe was the Cauſe of God, and that whoſoever died for it, received the Crown of Martyrdom; and by this very means did they encourage themſelves and their Party in their contempt of Magiſtrates, and put the <hi>Circumcellions</hi> on Maſſacres and the like moſt barbarous Outrages.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:105495:34"/>5. Their Seditious poſſeſſing the people with Jealouſies and Prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces againſt the good Emperor <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine:</hi> For inſtance,<note place="margin">Hiſt of <hi>Don.</hi> p. <hi>67.</hi>
                  </note> when he ſent <hi>Paulus</hi> and <hi>Macarius</hi> with his gifts and largeſſes about <hi>Africa,</hi> and with them his own Effigies, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending nothing hereby, but ſome Expreſſion of his good Affection to the people, and his endeavour of promoting that Peace and Unity in the Church, which he ſo extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſired: Theſe <hi>Donatiſts</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, <hi>[as Schiſmaticks always uſe to put the worſt conſtruction on their Princes beſt Actions]</hi> brute it all over <hi>Africa,</hi> that the Emperor had ſent Images to be ſet upon the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, and that he was ſetting up Idolatry and Superſtition in the Churches.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That which conduced as much as any thing to the growth and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of this Schiſm, was the great Toleration and Liberty that they enjoyed, and the want of Laws inflicted rigorouſly upon them:
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:105495:35"/>
Thus <hi>Danaeus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cap. 69.</note> 
                  <hi>Gregory</hi> the great, complains (ſaies he) of the Biſhops and Magiſtrates of his time, that this grievous and peſtilent Error of the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> did ſo long prevail and infeſt the Church, through their fault and negligence; it being heavy Penalties laid upon them, that muſt reduce them; this (he ſaies) did effectually Suppreſs them formerly, when <hi>Arcadius</hi> and <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius</hi> were Emperors.</p>
               <p>To all this may be added innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable inſtances of ſecret Fraud, and open Violence, as the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry means of promoting the Schiſm, ſuch as that of <hi>Ingentius</hi>'s forging Letters, containing the Teſtimony of <hi>Alfius Cecilianus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hiſt. of <hi>Don.</hi>
                  </note> concerning <hi>Faelix</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Aptung</hi>'s being a <hi>Traditor,</hi> and other the like in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, which made the Emperor call this Sect, <hi>Officinam Diaboli,</hi> when they were convicted of Schiſm in the Council of <hi>Arles.</hi> So alſo their beating and kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling any that oppoſed them; yea,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:105495:35"/>
or that were not of their wicked Party and Perſwaſion, ſaies <hi>Danae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Obvius ſibi quoſque in plateis &amp; agris homines à ſuis erroribus alienos caedunt &amp; jugulant furiosè,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cap. 69.</note> 
                  <hi>maximè ij qui inter eos Circumcelliones appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantur.</hi> In a word, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their greateſt Pretenſions to Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Holineſs above all others, they ſtuck at nothing (tho ever ſo barbarous and flagitious) to ſtrengthen their Party, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote their Schiſmatical intereſt; which they did ſuccesfully, till the good Emperors <hi>Conſtantine, Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius, Arcadius, &amp;c.</hi> put a ſtop to, and ſuppreſſed them by the ſame infallible means and method that Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> did the Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks of her time, <hi>(viz.)</hi> by ſtrict Laws made againſt them, and executed ſeverely on them. So ſaith the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian,<note place="margin">Sozom. <hi>Hiſt. Eccl.</hi> l. 2. <hi>c.</hi> 30. <hi>Hiſt. trip.</hi> l. 3. c. 11,</note> 
                  <hi>Conſtantine the first Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrian Emperor, finding the Church diſturbed by Schiſms, made a Law against all Conventicles, by which Law the Memory of Schiſmaticks
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:105495:36"/>
was deſtroyed</hi> (ſpeaking of the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſts</hi> only:) And St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Vincentius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ep.</hi> 48. <hi>Let.</hi> U.</note> 
                  <hi>Mine own City</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>which was wholly ſchiſmatical, of</hi> Donatus<hi>'s party, is now converted to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Church, by the fear of the</hi> Imperial Laws, <hi>and do ſo perfectly detest their former ſtubborneſs, that you can ſcarce believe them ever to have been guilty. To ſome of theſe</hi> (Donatiſts) <hi>the terror of the</hi> Imperial Laws <hi>hath been ſo profitable,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Let.</hi> X.</note> 
                  <hi>that they have thanked God for it; ſaying, God be thanked that hath quickened us by the Terror of the Laws, to ſeek what formerly we did not care to find; others ſay, We were frighten'd by falſe Rumors from coming into the Church, which we ſhould never have known to be falſe, if we had not come to Church; and we ſhould never have come to Church, if we had not been compelled.</hi> Thus did the Execution of Penal Laws, <hi>[when all other means failed]</hi> effectually Suppreſs them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:105495:36"/>But when <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate,<note place="margin">Aug. <hi>Ep.</hi> 166.</note> Emperor, deſigning thereby <hi>[among other expedients]</hi> to root out Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, gave them Toleration, the Schiſm revived, and the Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks grew numerous. And as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Schiſmaticks in 48, when they got Liberty and full Power in their hands, were preſently di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into <hi>Independents, Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, Quakers, Seekers, High-at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers, &amp;c.</hi> So theſe <hi>Donatiſts</hi> had no ſooner got Liberty by the Emperors Indulgence, but they were preſently divided, and ſubdivided (as in St. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> Epiſtles <hi>paſſim</hi>) into,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Luciferians,</hi> ſo called from their Ringleader, <hi>Lucifer Calarita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Sardinia;</hi> theſe dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered from the reſt of the <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists,</hi> on the account of rebap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing;<note place="margin">Dan. <hi>on</hi> Aug. <hi>de</hi> Haereſ. <hi>c.</hi> 69, 81.</note> the other <hi>Donatists</hi> opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning that in the Catholick Churches there were no true Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtes, and conſequently no true
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:105495:37"/>
Sacraments, [<hi>The efficacy of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament</hi> (ſay they) <hi>depending upon the dignity and ſanctity of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister</hi>] did rebaptize all that they received into Communion, and (which ſhews from whence the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptists</hi> did ariſe) refuſed to Baptize Children; <hi>Lucifer Calaritanus</hi> dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering from them in this, heads a party that ſeparated from other <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natists,</hi> called from their Ringleader <hi>Luciferians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Another Sect or Faction among the <hi>Donatists,</hi> were the <hi>Maximia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists,</hi> who ſeparated from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Donatists,</hi> as well as from the Catholicks, on pretence of greater Purity; they were ſo called from <hi>Maximianus</hi> their Ringleader, who diſcontented at <hi>Primitianas</hi>'s being preferred before him to the <hi>Pſeudo</hi>-Biſhoprick of <hi>Carthage,</hi> refuſed to hold Communion with his Fellow-<hi>Donatists,</hi> as well as Catholicks, and drew many after him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. From theſe ſprang up ſoon after, the <hi>Rogatians</hi> and <hi>Claudia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists,</hi>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:105495:37"/>
who were otherwiſe called <hi>Montenſes Campitae</hi> and <hi>Rupitani,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. <hi>c.</hi> 69.</note> from thoſe Fields and Caves where they kept their Conventicles; they were much what the ſame with our <hi>Engliſh Quakers. Optatus</hi> ſpeaks of them thus, <hi>Salutationis officium auferunt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>&amp; ne ave dicunt cuique noſtrum.</hi> They ſalute none of the Orthodox when they meet them, nor ſo much as bid them God ſpeed. Thus did Toleration and Liberty, make them divide and ſubdivide; every Schiſmatick being ready to ſet up for himſelf, as ſoon as the Schiſm is made; <hi>Danaeus</hi> mentions two other Sects among the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> the <hi>Permenianiſts</hi> and the <hi>Cirtenſes,</hi> beſides the <hi>Circumcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians;</hi> ſuch a ſuperfetation there is in Schiſm, wherever it is tolerated: And as all Schiſmaticks, when to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated and indulged, do uſually commence Hereticks in the end; what St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaid of <hi>Donatiſts</hi> himſelf,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>De</hi> Haereſ. <hi>c.</hi> 69.</note> his Commentator ſaid of his Followers: <hi>Arianis conſentiunt,</hi>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:105495:38"/>
as the <hi>Meletians</hi> did before them, they at laſt turned <hi>Arrians.</hi> Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther effect of their Toleration or Liberty, was the many barbarous outrages that they committed upon the Orthodox, as oft as Toleration empowered them; for inſtance, <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>textatus</hi> a <hi>Donatiſt</hi> Biſhop, being dead, <hi>Rogatus</hi> a man of note for his great Learning and good Life, was choſe in his ſtead; who, after the Election declared himſelf to be a Catholick, whereupon they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted him grievouſly, cauſing the <hi>Circumcellians</hi> to pull out his Tongue, and to cut off his Hand: They dragged <hi>Reſtitutus</hi> a Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> de geſtis cum. Emerit.</note> through a Channel of Mud, and after twelve days cruel Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment killed him: They murdered <hi>Maximianus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Vaga</hi> in like manner for nothing, but demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them the Poſſeſſion of a Church, which they had took of him, and which he recovered of them at Law: They put out the Eyes of others, and poured Lime and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:105495:38"/>
Vinegar in the Holes:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> Concreſc. <hi>Poſſid.</hi> in vit. <hi>Aug.</hi> in Hiſt. of the <hi>Don.</hi>
                  </note> They terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with Fire and Sword all the Churches of <hi>Africa,</hi> inſomuch that the Catholicks were afraid to Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel for fear of their <hi>Circumcellians:</hi> They not only ſilenced the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, but proclaimed it by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Cryer, that whoever did Communicate with <hi>Maximianus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. <hi>Ep.</hi> 166. <hi>lett.</hi> E.</note> ſhould have his houſe burnt: They laid wait for <hi>Poſſidius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Calame,</hi> with a deſign to kill him; and becauſe he eſcaped their Snares (as St. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> word is) they fired the houſe twice in which he took Sanctuary: The like outrages did theſe <hi>Pſeudo-Zealots</hi> commit upon <hi>Marcus</hi> a Presbyter of <hi>Caſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> on <hi>Marcianus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rgenſis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable others. In a word, ſo long as they had Power, no good Catholick that lived among them, could be ſecure of his Poſſeſſions or Life its ſelf;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>C.</hi> 62.</note> 
                  <hi>Obvios quoſque errori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſuis alienos</hi> (ſaies <hi>Danaeus:</hi>) all that were not of their Party and Opinion, they made no Conſcience
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:105495:39"/>
of Killing; and yet themſelve would cry out of Perſecution up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the leaſt touch of reſtraint. A further account of theſe <hi>Donatiſts</hi> may be ſeen in the 48, 50, 68, 166, 167, 168, 170, 171, 172. and others of St. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> Epiſtles, ſhewing the great agreement of the modern Schiſmaticks with thoſe of St <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines</hi> time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <hi>AERIANS</hi> AND <hi>PRESBYTERIANS.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PRESBYTERIANS</hi> were ſo called at firſt, for the great ſhare that they aſſigned to the Lay-Elders in the Government of the Church and State, as alſo for a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity that they would have among Miniſters, or a Coaequality between
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:105495:39"/>
Biſhops and Presbyters: The <hi>Greek</hi> word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is beſt rendred an Order of Elders, an Eccleſiaſtical Senate or Claſis, and ſo the word <hi>Presbyterian</hi> ſignifies one that is for the Government of the Church by Lay-Elders: But cuſtom (which commands the propriety of words) has made it appropriate to ſuch Proteſtants as are for a Parity among Miniſters, in oppoſition to Epiſcopal Government.</p>
               <p>Some perhaps may frame the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination from <hi>Aerius,</hi> the firſt of that Opinion; thus <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, old <hi>Aerius,</hi> or Presbyter <hi>Aerius,</hi> who was the firſt of any Sect that ſtood up for a Parity among Miniſters in oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Epiſcopacy, which was on this occaſion.<note place="margin">Dan. <hi>on</hi> Aug. <hi>de</hi> Haereſ. <hi>c.</hi> 53.</note> 
                  <hi>Aerius</hi> being or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained Presbyter by <hi>Eustathius</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Sebastia,</hi> was afterward by the Biſhop made Maſter of an Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, as I underſtand thoſe words of <hi>Danaeus [Ptochodocheio preficitur.]</hi> The Biſhop controuling him in the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:105495:40"/>
managery of the Hoſpital. He firſt quarrels the Biſhop, and then ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates from him, broaching this Error. <hi>Presbyterum ab Epiſcopo</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>ordine &amp; gradu non differre, ſed qui Presbyter est, Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copum dici, &amp;c.</hi> that a Biſhop and a Presbyter differ not, either in Order or Degree, but that a Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter is a Biſhop, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> On which very account <hi>Danaeus</hi> himſelf, tho a ſworn Enemy to Epiſcopacy, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes that <hi>Epiphanius, Auguſtine,</hi> and <hi>Iſidore</hi> accounted him and his Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, Hereticks, <hi>Aerianos Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticorum albo aſcripſere,</hi> Epiph. Aug. <hi>&amp;</hi> Iſid. <hi>in eo quod Presbyteri &amp; Epiſcopi parem dignitatem conſtitue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt;</hi> and <hi>Epiphanius</hi> [Adv. <hi>Aeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi>] calls the <hi>Aerians,</hi> the moſt brainſick Hereticks that ever were, for holding that Presbyters may ordain Presbyters, and that Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Presbyters were all one.</p>
               <p>About the Year 1561. the <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:105495:40"/>
began to be called <hi>Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans,</hi> on this account; Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> having publiſhed a Book of Orders, injoining ſtrict Conformity to the Orders and Diſcipline of the Church, in Oppoſition to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery and Presbytery both: Such as proceeded in Oppoſition to the Queens Injunctions relating to Presbytery, or Nonconformity, were called <hi>Puritans</hi> (as the <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatians</hi> were <hi>Catheri</hi>) as men pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing the greater purity in the Worſhip of God, which they placed chiefly in a ſhew of great Deteſtation of the Ceremonies and Corruptions of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> above other men. But taking the word <hi>(Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian)</hi> in its firſt and moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Acceptation, for all ſuch Proteſtants as are for a Parity among Miniſters in Oppoſition to Epiſcopacy, and to ſuch Church-Ceremonies as the Epiſcopal Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment requires, there is this following account given of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:105495:41"/>Their firſt riſe was in <hi>Geneva,</hi> a City not above two miles compaſs, governed by a Duke,<note place="margin">Heyl. <hi>Hiſt. of Presb.</hi> l. 1. n. 2. n. 4.</note> and a Biſhop, chiefly a Biſhop; who as Mr. <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> confeſſes, had not only the Eccleſiaſtical, but Civil Juriſdiction over it, till <hi>Viretus</hi> and <hi>Farellus,</hi> exceeding ſtudious of a Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Religion, laboureth with the Biſhop for ſuch Alteration as had been made in the Church of <hi>Berne:</hi> But not able to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with the Biſhop, they pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticed on the inferior ſort of People, and that ſo effectually, that in a tumultuous manner they drove the Biſhop and Clergy out of Town; and not only alter'd every thing that diſpleaſed them in the Church, but changed the Civil Government, diſclaiming all Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to their Biſhop or Duke ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> n. 4.</note> for which rebellious At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievement, <hi>Calvin</hi> calls <hi>Farellus,</hi> the Father of the publick Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:105495:41"/>The Government of the City being thus put into the hands of the Common People by the endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of <hi>Farellus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>N.</hi> 5:</note> Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> was choſe one of the Preachers of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva,</hi> and ſoon after Divinity-Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; which done, he preſently ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiates with them to abjure all O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to their Biſhop for the time to come,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Beza</hi> on the Life of <hi>Calvin.</hi>
                  </note> and to admit of ſuch a form of Diſcipline, as he and his Colleagues had deviſed for them; And having prevailed herein, the ſaid Diſcipline <hi>(viz.)</hi> the <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian</hi> Diſcipline, was generally ſworn and ſubſcribed to, on <hi>July</hi> 20. 1537, the very ſame Year (as I remember) that the Order of <hi>Jeſuits</hi> was founded; and this was the firſt Extract of Presbytery, as my Author ſays, begot in Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, born in Sedition, and nurſed up in Faction: No ſooner was it ſetled in <hi>Geneva,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hiſt. of Preſ. lib. <hi>1.</hi> n. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> but <hi>Calvins</hi> next endeavours were to promote it in other places, which he did effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly [notwithſtanding the Jars and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:105495:42"/>
that it occaſioned] by theſe and the like means.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>N.</hi> 11.</note>1. By the great Reputation that <hi>Calvin</hi> had attained to, for his dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in Preaching and Writing, whereby he became the Oracle of the Times.</p>
               <p n="2">2. His impoſing it on the People, on pain of Gods high diſpleaſure; and <hi>Beza</hi> after him, making it as unlawful to recede from the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Diſcipline, as from the moſt Material Points in the Chriſtian Faith.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Self-ends and Ambition of ſome Miniſters, affecting the Parochial Epiſcopacy, or Supreme Miniſterial Power in their own Pariſhes.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Covetouſneſs of ſome Great Perſons, who thought there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to raiſe to themſelves great for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes by the Spoils of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricks; and for the attainment of theſe Ends, they ſtuck at nothing, whether the depoſing of Kings, or ſubverting the Fundamental Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:105495:42"/>
of all Civil States where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they came; and it's obſervable, that that very thing which the Engliſh Diſſenters at this day inſiſt on, as the <hi>Articulus Stantis vel ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentis Presbyter,</hi> the very <hi>baſis</hi> on which their Nonconformity doth ſtand, <hi>[as Popery doth on the infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility]</hi> was the main rule which <hi>Calvin</hi> went by in all his Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion work <hi>[viz.] That there ought to be nothing (and conſequently no ceremony) in the Worſhip of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>n.</hi> 3.</note> 
                  <hi>which is not warranted and required in Gods Word, or which hath not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular and expreſs command in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for its uſe:</hi> An Error which Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> himſelf hath ſoundly confuted by many ſubſtantial Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in his <hi>Defence of the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Love,</hi> Part 1. p. 97, 98, 99, 100, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> having compleated the ſettlement of his new Diſcipline in <hi>Geneva</hi> about the Year 1541. thought himſelf of ſuch grand aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that no Church could be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:105495:43"/>
without his interpoſal; He offers his Aſſiſtance to Arch-Biſhop <hi>Cranmer,</hi> as ſoon as he heard of the Reformation intended here in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland;</hi> but the Arch-Biſhop know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Man, refuſed the offer; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he took Order with <hi>Martin Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer</hi> at his firſt coming into <hi>England</hi> to give him ſome account of the Engliſh Liturgy; which was no ſooner done, but he preſently makes thoſe Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which afterward became the main ground of thoſe many Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, thoſe horrible Diſorders and Confuſions with which his Faction had involved the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> from that Time to this.</p>
               <p>Prevailing nothing with that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Martyr, he tampers with the Lord Protector, with the King himſelf, and the Lords of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil; had his Agents in the City and Country,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>N.</hi> 15, 16.</note> the Univerſities and Convocations; all of them Practiſing in their Several Provinces to decry the uſe of Kneeling, the Croſs at Baptiſm, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and to bring the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:105495:43"/>
People to a diſlike of the Common-Prayer-Book; which at its firſt compoſure was looked on by the People generally as a Heavenly Treaſure (ſays Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> in his Acts and Monum. Preface) ſent down by God in great Mercy to the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Nation; all moderate Men beyond Sea applauding the Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the <hi>Englanders</hi> in having ſuch an Excellent form of Gods Publick Worſhip:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>n.</hi> 3.</note> And an Act of Parliament declared it compoſed by the ſpecial Aid and Aſſiſtance of the Holy-Ghoſt: But all Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> could do, would avail nothing, nor could his Presbyterian Diſcipline get any footing in <hi>England,</hi> till</p>
               <p n="1">1. Popery introduced it by <hi>Queen Mary's</hi> baniſhing moſt of the moſt Eminent of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Divines into <hi>Embden, Baſil,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The firſt riſe of Preſ. out of Popery.</note> 
                  <hi>Strasburgh, Geneva, Frankford,</hi> and where the Presbyterian Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and Government was; from whence they returned into <hi>England</hi>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:105495:44"/>
tainted when the Perſecution was over,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>n.</hi> 14.</note> and had preferment gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them in the Churches, whereby they got opportunity of preparing the minds of People for ſuch inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, as they hoped (when Time ſerved) to bring into the Church; But the Fabrick of the State was joined together with ſuch ligaments of Power and Wiſdom, that they were able to act but little, and to effect leſs.</p>
               <p>About this Time died <hi>Calvin,</hi> having ſat 28 Years in the Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors Chair at <hi>Geneva,</hi> and was ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded in the ſame Year, 1564. by <hi>Beza,</hi> who [tho at laſt he recanted very far] at firſt endeavoured the ſettlement of the Presbytery in <hi>England</hi> with more Zeal and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs than <hi>Calvin</hi> had done. He preſently brought it to an open Schiſm, and a reſort to Conventicles, which himſelf takes notice of in a Letter to Biſhop <hi>Grindal, Rem tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem in pertinax ſchiſma evaſiſſe — Nonnulli tam ſeorſim ſuos caetus ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent,</hi>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:105495:44"/>
&amp;c. Bez. Ep. 23.</p>
               <p>Having by this means got ſome footing in <hi>England, [as alſo by the connivence of ſome Biſhops, and by the Queens indulgence to'ards them, particularly in tolerating the French church in</hi> London, <hi>where the</hi> Geneva <hi>diſcipline was exerciſed</hi>] they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſo inſolent, as to publiſh thoſe peſtilent Pamphlets called the <hi>Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions,</hi> wherein they proceeded ſo far, as to tell the Parliament, that it ſhould be more tolerable for <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> than for them; and that if they would not coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance the <hi>Geneva</hi> Diſcipline, themſelves would be their own car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>n.</hi> 23. 24.</note> Whereupon the Queen iſſued forth her Proclamation for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuppreſſing of them; ſo that by means of the Rigor of the Laws, the Government being too ſtrong for them, their next Expedient was,</p>
               <p n="2">2. To diſſemble Conformity,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>n.</hi> 33, 34, 35.</note> thinking thereby to breed up their Presbytery under the Wing of Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:105495:45"/>
till it ſhould be ſtrong e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to ſubſiſt of it ſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 8. <hi>n.</hi> 24, 26</note>Next they proceed to libel the Government with ſuch ridiculing Pamphlets, as <hi>Mar-prelate, Ha' y' any work for the cooper; the Epiſtle to the Confocation houſe,</hi> &amp;c. in which they far exceeded the railings of the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> againſt the Catholicks; calling the Arch-Biſhop, <hi>Pope of Lambeth, and Belzeebub</hi> of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury;</hi> the reſt of the Biſhops, <hi>petty Popes, and cogging Knaves,</hi> &amp;c. and the reſt of the Clergy, worſe.</p>
               <p>To ſtop the Mouths of theſe <hi>Rabſhakehs,</hi> there were ſeveral grave Refutals given, but all in vain, till <hi>Tom. Naſh</hi> the Obſervator of thoſe Times, a man of <hi>Sarcaſtick</hi> Wit, by ſome Pamphlets written in the ſame looſe way [ſuch as the <hi>Paſquil, the Counterſcuffle, Pap with the Hatchet,</hi> &amp;c. ſtopped their Mouths for ever medling more in that way.</p>
               <p>About the Year 1592. they were buſie in petitioning the Queen.
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:105495:45"/>
Their Petitions were ſuch as gave the Queen a full aſſurance of what reſtleſs Spirits they were,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 9. <hi>N.</hi> 22.</note> and that no quiet was to be expected, till they were utterly ſuppreſſed: In order thereto a Parliament was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; at their firſt Sitting, the Queen ſignified it to both Houſes, that they ſhould keep themſelves to the redreſs of popular Grievances, but that they ſhould leave all matters of State to Her and Her Council, and all Eccleſiaſtcal matters to Her and Her Biſhops: But contrary to her Command, Mr. <hi>Peter Wentworth,</hi> a Member of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and a great Zealot for the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Diſcipline, with Mr. <hi>Bromley,</hi> and others of the Houſe of Commons, deliver'd a Petition to the Lord Keeper <hi>Puckering,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring that the Lords would joyn with them of the lower Houſe, in becoming Suppliants to the Queen, for <hi>entailing the Succeſſion of the Crown,</hi> according to a Bill which they had prepared: At this the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:105495:46"/>
Queen was ſo diſpleaſed, that Mr. <hi>Wentworth</hi> was ſent to the Tower; Mr. <hi>Bromley</hi> and ſome others of the Commons, committed to the <hi>Fleet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>N.</hi> 25.</note>In this Parliament it was enacted, that, <hi>If any Perſon ſhould come to, or be at any unlawful Aſſemblies, Conventicles, or Meetings, under pretence of Religious exerciſe, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Laws and Statutes made in that behalf,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that every Perſon ſo offending ſhould be committed to Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, without Bail or Mainpriſe, or depart the Realm at ſuch time and place as was aſſigned, with this</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſo,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>N.</hi> 27.</note> 
                  <hi>that if he departed not at the time appointed, or come back without leave firſt granted, he ſhould ſuffer Death, as in the caſe of</hi> Felony. And when all other means failed, theſe ſharp Laws made againſt them, and ſome ſevere Executions done upon them, humbled the Ringlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of them, ruined the whole <hi>Machina</hi> of their devices, and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:105495:46"/>
promoted the Peace and Tranquillity of Church and State, and the happy Preſervation of Her Majeſties Perſon, to a proſperous and peaceable Reign.</p>
               <p>And 'tis believed, that at King <hi>James</hi>'s firſt coming to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> about the year 1603, the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> in both Kingdoms, <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> were brought ſo low,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 11. <hi>N.</hi> 1.</note> that they might have been ſuppreſſed for ever without any great danger, had that King held the Reins with a ſteady hand, and not remitted ſo much <hi>[as he did]</hi> in the cares and ſeverities of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; particularly, in admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the <hi>Presbyterian</hi>-petitioning, and eſpecially, in that called the Millenary-petition, becauſe ſaid to be Subſcribed by a thouſand hands, when indeed it wanted ſome hundreds of it: This Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was for Reformation of ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry Ceremonies and Abuſes, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Croſs in Baptiſm, Church-Muſick,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:105495:47"/>
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which occaſioned the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence at <hi>Hampton Court,</hi> where the King himſelf was preſent as Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>N.</hi> 6.</note> between the Epiſcopal and <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Divines; the reſult of the conference was this ſharp re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primand<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>If this be all they have to ſay</hi> (ſaies the King) <hi>I'le make them conform,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Conf. at</hi> Hamp. Court, <hi>p.</hi> 85.</note> 
                  <hi>or I'le hurry them out of the Kingdom;</hi> or ſomewhat worſe, at the concluſion of the conference. The <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, when they ſaw that they could not obtain their deſires in ſuch Conceſſions and Alterations, as they diſputed for; they were (notwithſtanding) not tranſported with heat and paſſion, or any ſuch bigottery, as the modern Diſſenters are, on ſuch occaſion; but ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly promiſed the Biſhops, their Antagoniſts, <hi>That they would never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs reverence them as ſpiritual Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and joyn with them againſt the common Enemy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:105495:47"/>Upon this Conference,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>N.</hi> 8.</note> the Kings Proclamation was iſſued forth, commanding ſtrict Conformity, and admoniſhing all his Subjects of what ſort ſoever, Never after to expect any Alteration in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick form of Gods Worſhip; and things being accordingly put in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, and the Government hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a hard hand upon them, incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity ſoon grew out of faſhion again,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>N.</hi> 10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Till the <hi>Gunpowder-Treaſon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">N <hi>12.</hi> Presbytery out of Popery, the ſecond time.</note> from whence they took occaſion to poſſeſs the People with fears and jealouſies of new dangers from the <hi>Papiſts;</hi> and by a ſhew of greateſt Zeal for the Proteſtant Religion, they got a Party in the Houſe of Commons, who by the ſpecious pretences of ſtanding for the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects Property, and the Preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Proteſtant Religion, weakened the Prerogative Royal, and advanced their own; and by degrees, got ſo ſtrong in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:105495:48"/>
that at the beginning of the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, they were able to proceed from Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil to Execution; beginning their Embroilments firſt in <hi>Scotland,</hi> by ſending thither the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liturgy, and Book of Canons;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sir</hi> R. Bak. <hi>Anno</hi> 1638.</note> whereupon the <hi>Scots</hi> took up Arms, declaring not to lay them down, till the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Religion was ſetled in both Nations; they being incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged ſo to do, by ſome of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Parliament;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> 1640.</note> which the King underſtanding, went to the Houſe of Commons, to demand five of their Members, whom he accuſed of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious Intercourſe had with the <hi>Scots</hi> in that Inſurrection. And here began the firſt Eruption.</p>
               <p>The King wanting Money to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage the War with <hi>Spain,</hi> was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to have almoſt continual Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, of which many Members be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Scotized, fell preſently on Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Ship money unlawful, the Convocation of the Clergy Illegal,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:105495:48"/>
and their Canons void;<note place="margin">Bak. <hi>Chron.</hi> 1641. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> paſſed a Bill for taking away the Biſhops Votes in Parliament; [<hi>Which when the King conſented to,</hi> he ſaies, <hi>he never enjoyed comfortable day after</hi>] they paſſed a Bill for a Triennial Parliament, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All which they forced from the King, by terror of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Army, which they kept in pay nine Months on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: And tho the Lords and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers at <hi>York,</hi> in their Declaration,<note place="margin">Bak. <hi>Chron.</hi> 1642.</note> proteſted before God, and teſtified to all the World (as they had often done before) that they were fully perſwaded that the King had no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to make War upon the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, but that all his endeavours tended to a firm Settlement of the Proteſtant Religion, the juſt Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of Parliament, the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Subject, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet they proceeded <hi>[chiefly on pretence of the fear of Popery]</hi> to wreſt the <hi>Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi> out of his hand, as alſo the <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> the <hi>Navy Royal,</hi> and all his Revenues; uſing all
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:105495:49"/>
Terror imaginable, to affright his Subjects from Supplying or Aſſiſting him: In ſhort, a rebellious and moſt unnatural War being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menced, which ſhed the Blood of ſo many thouſands, they reduced the King to conſent to theſe, and the like Propoſals;<note place="margin">Baker <hi>Chron. Anno</hi> 1648.</note> 
                  <hi>That the</hi> Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian <hi>Diſcipline ſhould be ſet up for three years</hi> [in the interim of which they would endeavour the Settlement of Peace in Church and State:] <hi>That the</hi> Militia <hi>ſhould be lodged into their hands for twenty years: That the whole Government of</hi> Ireland, <hi>both Military and Civil, ſhould be put into their hands: That they ſhould confer all Officers, and all chief Magiſtrates of the Kingdom of</hi> England <hi>for twenty years.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And having thus got the whole Soveraignty to themſelves, they were willing on theſe moſt unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Conceſſions, to comply with the King, and voted a full agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:105495:49"/>
with him: But alas, too late; they having by this time cut off his hands and feet, empowered the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent Army to cut off his Head: And now when the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Diſcipline was to be compleatly ſetled, the Army <hi>[which themſelves had raiſed]</hi> declare for the <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent</hi> Way, and ſerve them, as they had ſerved the King, turn them out of Doors, and reſolve upon nothing leſs then the Death of the King; which was at firſt attempted by private Conſpiracy, with Poyſon and Piſtol, by Captain <hi>Rolph,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Baker</hi>'s Chron. Anno <hi>1648.</hi>
                  </note> with the privity of Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>Hammond,</hi> and ſome other chief Officers of the Army: But afterwards effected with ſuch Hell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred Solemnity, and in ſuch barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous manner, as <hi>[to the everlaſting reproach of the Proteſtant Religion] Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars</hi> have ſtartled at: Thus did they wade through the Blood of men, the beſt of men, to deſtroy the Peace of the Church, and to ſet up that <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:105495:50"/>
which was no ſooner up but down, as that which will no more comport with the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government, than <hi>Popery</hi> or the <hi>Musſleman</hi> Faith. And as this barbarous Regicidy, ſo that which introduced it with ſo much Murder, Perjury and Rapine, I mean the Civil War, which coſt ſo many millions of Treaſury, and ſo many thouſands of Mens lives, was undeniably the effect of the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Schiſm; as is ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledged by the mouth of a modern Diſſenter, which is Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> a dying man, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be believed; ſpeaking to a Nonconformiſt (<hi>whom he doth ſo orthodoxly and honeſtly write againſt.]</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cathol. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion doubly Defended, <hi>p. 31.</hi>
                  </note>] <hi>If you know not</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>I do, that the principles of Separation were the great cauſe of the Subverſions and Confuſions which brought us to what we have felt — in</hi> England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>for theſe forty years; and if I may not have leave to ſay with</hi> Bradford, <hi>Repent O</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:105495:50"/>
                  <hi>you ſhould give me leave to repent my ſelf, that ever I preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one Sermon with any Biaſs of overmuch deſire to pleaſe Perſons of the accuſing ſeparating humour.</hi> Thus Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in that late, and laſt of all his Books. But to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</p>
               <p>In concluſion of this War and Regicidy, the men in Buff fell to Reformation-work in Churches, which I cannot but take notice of in this place, it being ſo exactly agreeable to the pattern of <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate's reforming Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: In <hi>Wincheſter</hi> Church, Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Waller</hi> with ſome of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hiſt. of Presb.</hi> lib. 13. n. 23.</note> threw down the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion Table, broke down the Rails, and burnt them in an Ale-houſe, ſtrewed the pavement of the Quire, with the Leaves which they tore out of the Common-prayer Book; and whereas the remains of ſeveral <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> Kings and Biſhops, had been [<hi>by the care of Biſhop</hi> Fox] gathered
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:105495:51"/>
into leaden Cheſts, they ſcattered the Duſt of their Bodies before the Wind, and threw their Bones about the Church; The very ſame that <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate did to the remains of <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt [<hi>buried at</hi> Samaria] <hi>He cauſed his Bones to be digged up, and being mixed with the Bones of Beaſts, he burnt them to Aſhes, and ſcattered the Aſhes before the Wind.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>N.</hi> 24, 25.</note>In the Cathedral Church of <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter,</hi> after they had picked out the Eyes of the portraitur'd King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth, ſaying in ſcorn, <hi>That all the miſchief came from him, in eſtabliſhing the Common-Prayer at firſt;</hi> they fell to pillaging and plundering, like the <hi>Goths</hi> at the Sack of <hi>Rome;</hi> and when it was beg'd that they would leave but one Chalice for the uſe of the Sacrament, it was anſwered, <hi>A wooden Diſh may ſerve turn:</hi> The ſame words almoſt, as of <hi>Faelix [Colleague to</hi> Julian, <hi>that renounced Chriſtianity in
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:105495:51"/>
complement</hi> to Julian] who taking up the Communion-plate, which the Religious <hi>Conſtantine</hi> had in piety beſtowed upon the Church, <hi>See here</hi> (ſaies he in ſcorn) <hi>what brave Cups and Veſſels the Son of</hi> Mary <hi>is ſerved in.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Church of <hi>Exeter</hi> they turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into a Jakes, leaving their filth on and about the Communion Table; whereas the Apoſtate <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lian</hi> did but piſs againſt the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion Table, in a Church at <hi>Antioch,</hi> and the Presbyter <hi>Euzoius</hi> reproved him (tho an Emperor) ſharply to his face. And in all this they wrote, as after the Copy of the Apoſtate <hi>Julian,</hi> ſo with the practice of the <hi>Donatiſt</hi>-Diſſenters. As <hi>Optatus</hi> relates, that in <hi>Thipaſa,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Opt. 55. <hi>ap. Hiſt. of</hi> Don.</note> a City of <hi>Mauritania,</hi> the barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Donatiſts</hi> aſſaulted an Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of the Orthodox Chriſtians, while they were at their Devotions, and driving them out of the Church, ſlew a great many of
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:105495:52"/>
them; the Bread of the conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Euchariſt, they threw to the Dogs, who having eaten it, by the juſt Judgment of God, preſently grew mad, fell upon their Maſters that gave it them, and tore them to pieces.</p>
               <p>But in the reforming the Church of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> they exceeded <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> or the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> either;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>N.</hi> 25.</note> for finding there ſome Figures of Chriſt in the <hi>Arras-hangings</hi> in the Quire, they did in the moſt literal Sence, crucifie Chriſt <hi>in Effigie;</hi> ſome ſwearing that they would ſtab him, others that they would rip up his Bowels, which accordingly they did, ſo far as the Figures of Chriſt in the Hangings were capable of it.</p>
               <p>The principal Inſtrument in framing this Reformation, and Hammering out all that miſchief of the War and Regicidy, was a Tool called the <hi>Solemn League
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:105495:52"/>
and Covenant;</hi> as appears by the dying words of one of the chief contrivers of it, Sir <hi>Henry Vane,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Speech</hi> p. 3.</note> at his Execution on <hi>Tower-Hill: That what the Houſe of Commons did ſingly by themſelves (which was their Levying of War, Murdering the King, proſcribing his Son, Voting down Monarchy) with much more which, he ſaies, lay yet in the breaſt of the Houſe, was but a more refined purſuit of the Covenant:</hi> Thus Sir <hi>Henry Vane,</hi> who being ſent hence Commiſſioner into <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> was one of the firſt Contrivers of it; and therefore moſt likely to know the uſe and deſign of it; and being then ready to die, was moſt likely to ſpeak truth.</p>
               <p>But thus much is demonſtrably true, that the <hi>Covenant</hi> put them on altering the Government, and that Alteration on the aforeſaid Reformation; as alſo upon War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring againſt the King, and that
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:105495:53"/>
War upon conquering, and that Conqueſt upon Impriſoning, and that Impriſoning upon Impowering a rude Conquering Army to Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him: So that their laying all on a rude conquering Army (as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> doth) is no other Plea for the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> not kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the King,<note place="margin">Plea for Peace.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> than <hi>Pilates</hi> was, for his Innocency in putting Chriſt to Death, becauſe he left the Execution of it to the Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: But to ſhew what an Engine this Covenant was againſt the Church; what a Solemn piece of Perjury, and what a ſnare of Souls, what a myſtery of Iniquity, and what a bane of Monarchy, 'tis fit all Poſterity ſhould be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in theſe three Articles of it:</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That without reſpect of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, they would endeavour to extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate Popery and Prelacy,</hi> i. e. <hi>Church-Government by Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Deans,</hi> &amp;c. and all this not only
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:105495:53"/>
contrary to the Kings Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſtrictly forbidding it; but contrary to an Oath previouſly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by a great part of the <hi>Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>That they would endeavour the diſcovery of all ſuch as had been, or ſhould be Incendiaries, Malignants, evil Inſtruments,</hi> &amp;c. whereby they bound themſelves and others (as the event ſhew'd) to bear falſe againſt, to Condemn and Murder the Kings beſt Friends, as thoſe that ſtood moſt in their way, as the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> Arch-Biſhop <hi>Laud,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>That they would preſerve the Kings Perſon in the preſervation of the true</hi> [i. e. Presbyterian Religion] <hi>and the Liberties of this Kingdom:</hi> Which was in effect a covenanting to Rebel againſt the King, if not to Murder him, in regard that the Covenanters had already declared from Pulpit and Preſs, that the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:105495:54"/>
Religion and Worſhip eſtabliſhed in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the King, was Popiſh and Idolatrous; and that the <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> was the only true Religion; and that the King had actually in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded the Liberties of the Subjects, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and on this account, this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle took in its limitations, did in effect empower them to abſolve themſelves from their Allegiance, and to take up Arms againſt the King: So that if we conſider this Covenant in theſe four circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the Subject-matter of it, the Deſign and Occaſion of it, the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons engaged in it, and the manner of Imploying it; it will appear to be,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Farewel Serm.</hi> p. 37.</note> not only as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> calls it, <hi>A dividing Engine, an impoſing on the Providence of God,</hi> &amp;c. but as another Nonconformiſt called it, <hi>A very neſt of Villany;</hi> and as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them,<note place="margin">Nar. of the Covenant.</note> 
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Phil. Nye, <hi>Such a Covenant as was never heard, nor read of, nor ever the World ſaw;</hi> and as yet this was made the Teſt of all
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:105495:54"/>
ſuch as were to be truſted or accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: And of the ſame ſtamp with theſe old Covenantiers are there great numbers at this day, <hi>The cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain men among us crept in unawares,</hi> of whom Dr. <hi>Hickes</hi> gives this em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatical Mark,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Serm. at</hi> Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt May 29. <hi>Preface.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>That are for the King againſt his evil Councellors, and for the Proteſtant Religion againſt the Church:</hi> Of their barbarous Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties to'ards the Orthodox Clergy, and others (wherein they exceeded the Cruelties of the <hi>Donatists</hi> to'ards the Orthodox Clergy of thoſe times) ſee <hi>Aerius Rediv.</hi> lib. 13. <hi>Mercurius Ruſticus,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>No ſooner had they battered down Epiſcopacy by their <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> Ordinances, and ſet up Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery in its ſtead; but that beloved Diſcipline and Government [<hi>whoſe ſettlement in</hi> England <hi>coſt ſo many millions of Treaſure, and ſo many thouſands of Lives</hi>] in the turn of a hand was made <hi>ſub</hi> to Independency, and that ſoon dwindled into more Sects, than ever old <hi>Donatiſm</hi> was;
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:105495:55"/>
ſuch as <hi>Anabaptists, Quakers, Seek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, High-Attainers,</hi> &amp;c. Some of which would in all probability have become the prevailing Religion of the Nation, had not the ſeaſonable Reſtoration of King <hi>Charles</hi> the 2d prevented it: By all which we are taught to look on it, as what God hath written to us in Characters of Blood, <hi>That no other than the Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal Government will comport with the Conſtitution of the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to ſhew yet further, the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement of theſe men with the <hi>Donatists,</hi> and other Sectaries of old; I ſhall conclude this Head with that Character which King <hi>James</hi> gave of them, <hi>That tho they refuſed to be called</hi> Anabaptiſts;<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>yet they partook too much of their humour; not only agreeing with them in that general Rule, the contempt of the Civil Magiſtrate, and in leaning to their Dreams, Imaginations, and (pretended) Revelations; but par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:105495:55"/>
in accounting all men pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, that agree not to their Fancies, in making as much commotion for every particular queſtion of Church-polity, as if an Article of the Trinity were called in queſtion; in making the Scripture to be ruled by their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and not their Conſcience by the Scripture; in accounting every one as a</hi> Heathen <hi>and</hi> Publican, <hi>and not worthy to enjoy the benefit of breathing, much leſs to partake with them in the Sacraments, that denies the leaſt jot of their ground: And in ſuffering the King, People, Law, and all to be trodden under foot, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the leaſt of their Grounds be impugned: He stiles them the very Pests of the Commonwealth, whom no deſerts can oblige, breathing out nothing but Calumnies and Sedition; Aſpiring without Meaſure, Railing without Reaſon, and making their own Imaginations the ſquare of their Conſciences.</hi> Thus doth King <hi>James</hi> Characterize the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> of his time, exactly agreeing in every
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:105495:56"/>
clauſe of the Character, with the <hi>Donatists,</hi> and the reſt of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Schiſmaticks. To all which he ſubjoins in the form of a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation, <hi>That one ſhall never find in any High-landers, or bordering Thieves, greater Ingratitude, more Lies and Perjuries, than among theſe Phanatick Spirits,</hi> (as he calls them:) And becauſe the <hi>Novatians,</hi> the <hi>Donatists,</hi> and other Schiſmaticks of old, as well as of late, have had the Denomination (of Phanaticks) given them; and becauſe 'tis a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that I have obſerved to be groſly miſunderſtood, even by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great pretenders to knowledg, eſpecially of the Diſſenters, I ſhall ſubjoin this brief account of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:105495:56"/>
               <head>PHANATICISM.</head>
               <p>THE word is uſed to ſignifie (falſe) pretenſions to Divine motion,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> or Inſpiration from God; and is appropriate to thoſe, who in matters of Religion, inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle God to Enthuſiaſtick Fancies, aſcribe their whimſical perſwaſions, unaccountable Humours, and Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtick Motions, to the Suggeſtion and Impulſe of the bleſſed Spirit of God; that to defend an (other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe indefenſenſible Cauſe, pretend to the <hi>aliquid</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſome impulſe or motion from God: Thus <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus,</hi> when he had a mind to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage the <hi>Circumcellians</hi> in any barbarous deſign, his cuſtom was to pretend that an Angel had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to him, and aſſured him
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:105495:57"/>
of immediate Anſwer to his Prayers, for the Confirmation of his Party, <hi>Oravit Donatus, &amp; reſpondit ei deus</hi> (ſaies <hi>Optatus.</hi>)</p>
               <p n="1">1. The groſſeſt ſort of Phana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiſm is of thoſe, who pretend to the <hi>aliquid</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the impulſe of Gods Spirit, for things in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſinful; when men do inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle God to ſuch Villanies, as Fraud, Treaſon, Sedition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As that of <hi>Donatus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> Ep. <hi>165.</hi> &amp; paſſim.</note> who would pretend to conference with an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, and Revelation from God, telling the <hi>Circumcellions,</hi> that he would ſeek God, and give them Directions, when he had a mind to put them on any Maſſacre, Rapine, or the like. Of this ſort was the <hi>Scotch</hi> Mrs. <hi>Mitchelſon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Spirit of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery out of the mouth of Phanat.</note> whom the Presbyterians of <hi>Scotland</hi> ſet up for a Propheteſs; She pretended to be inſpired, and that it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to her by God, that the Solemn League and Covenant was
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:105495:57"/>
approved of by him, and ratified in Heaven:<note place="margin">Speech at his Execution.</note> So <hi>Kid [a Conventicle Preacher of</hi> Scotland, <hi>hanged for Sedition in the year</hi> 1680] his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the conceited ſtrength and number of the Rebels, <hi>the Lords power and preſence, and the ſtrong hand of the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. which is ſo far forth Phanaticiſm, as it is an intituling the Power and Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God to Rebellion: So al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>Coppinger</hi> in Queen <hi>Elizabeth's</hi> time, after a ſtrict Faſt [<hi>held for freeing of</hi> Cartwright, Snape, <hi>&amp;c. out of Priſon, and for ſucceſs in promoting the Presbyterian Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline</hi>] in his Journey to'ards <hi>Kent,</hi> he fancied,<note place="margin">Aeri. Red.</note> 
                  <hi>That he was admitted to a familiar conference with God, that he received many Directions from him, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly that God had ſhewed him a way to bring the Queen and all her Nobles to Repentance, or to prove them Traytors to God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:105495:58"/>
                  <note place="margin">Baker <hi>Chron. An.</hi> 1591.</note>Of this <hi>Coppingers</hi> School of Hypocriſie, was <hi>Hacket,</hi> a man of ſuch deſperate Malice, that bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an old Grudge to one that had been his Schoolmaſter, bit of his Noſe; when the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter begged that he may have it to ſow on again before it was cold,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hiſt. of Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byt.</hi> lib. 9. n. 6.</note> he chewed it with his Teeth, and ſwallowed it down: yet did this man attain to that eſteem among the People, and conceit of himſelf <hi>[by his counterfeit ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and extemporate Prayers]</hi> that at laſt, his pride improved into ſuch <hi>Phanaticiſm,</hi> as has ſcarce been heard of; pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to extraordinary Zeal for the Reformation; he pretended alſo to extraordinary Revelations from God, for the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it: He pretended that God had revealed to him, that there ſhould be no more Popes; that <hi>England</hi> would be that year, grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly afflicted with Plague and
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:105495:58"/>
Famine, unleſs the Reformation, and the Lords Diſcipline (mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Diſcipline) were admitted; he bruted abroad, that the Queen was an Uſurper, and the like Seditious Speeches; for which he was Hang'd and Quartered; about the ſame time, 1593. <hi>Penry</hi> was Hanged for the like ſeditious Practices, for which <hi>[in a</hi>
                  <note n="‖" place="margin">The Hiſt. of <hi>Korah, Dath.</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> Preface. Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript.</note> 
                  <hi>Book publiſhed ſoon after his Execution]</hi> he was ſtiled by the Diſſenters, <hi>A Martyr of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, a godly Man, Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Learned, Zealous, and of moſt Chriſtian Carriage and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, who ſuffer'd for writing for the Truth of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> In the ſame year <hi>Barrow,</hi> who was Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for condemning the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as no true Church,<note place="margin">Hiſt. of the Presbyt. <hi>l. 9.</hi>
                  </note> and Derogating from the Queens Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in matters Eccleſiaſtical, and the like ſeditious Practiſes; ſpeaking to Dr. <hi>Andrews,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Parry,</hi> after his Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:105495:59"/>
                  <hi>'Tis true</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi> Cranmer, <hi>Biſhop</hi> Ridley, <hi>and others, were Martyrs in Queen</hi> Mary<hi>'s days; but theſe bonds of mine</hi> [ſhaking his Fetters] <hi>are much more glorious then any of theirs, becauſe they had the mark of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt in their hands.</hi> And of the ſame ſort, are all who ſuffer on the account of Sedition, Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, and the like; and yet intitle God to thoſe Villanies, in calling their juſt Puniſhment, Perſecution, ſuffering for Righteouſneſs-ſake, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. There is a rank ſmatch of Phanaticiſm in that fundamental Article of the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Faith, <hi>That it is unlawful to uſe any thing in the Worſhip of God, which is not expreſly commanded by ſome Divine Law.</hi> If the belief of this be a fathering of our Sins upon God, then is it rank Phanaticiſm; but that the belief of this is a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:105495:59"/>
of our Sins upon God, is ſufficiently proved by Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> himſelf, in his <hi>Defence of the Principle of Love,</hi> Part 1. page 100.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A third Inſtance of Phana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiſm, is falſe pretenſion to the Spirit of God in Preaching, as among the Quakers, a Spawn of the Popiſh <hi>Franciſcans,</hi> who made unlearnedneſs a Profeſſion, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding themſelves in the Title of <hi>Fratres Ignorantiae;</hi> and among the Presbyterians,<note place="margin">Eraſm. <hi>Ep.</hi> 59. <hi>ad frat.</hi> Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</note> there is <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rellus</hi> of <hi>Geneva,</hi> the firſt lay-Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron of Presbytery, who in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion to the Spirit, called all humane learning, <hi>The invention of the Devil.</hi> Somewhat like Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers in Preaching, are ſome others, who in Preaching, take boiling Paſſion for holy Zeal; and wild Imagination for Divine Motion; when a fiery Fancy mounting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loft, flutters in myſtical Nonſence,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:105495:60"/>
and flows into the Tongue in extravagant Ramble, abuſing the Name and Word of God, with ſenſleſs Notions, phantaſtick Phraſes, and unintelligible Cant, and all this aſcribed to the bleſſed Spirit of God, as the extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Work of that adorable Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; and as Preaching by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ſo of writing by the Spirit, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in his Treatiſe of Epiſcopacy, <hi>P.</hi> 1. <hi>ch.</hi> 14. <hi>p.</hi> 169. gives this remarkable Inſtance, <hi>That there are many poor men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, divers Weavers and Ploughmen of his own Church at</hi> Kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derminſter,<note place="margin">To diſabuſe the Weavers of <hi>Kidderminſter</hi> in this matter, I muſt Inſert in their behalf, that I know them to be for the moſt part men of ſuch Moderation and Sobriety in Judgment, as to diſdain ſuch Flattery, and reſent ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> here offers them.</note> 
                  <hi>who are able, not only to Pray and Teach, as well as moſt of thoſe (Biſhops and Fathers of the Church) who are by</hi> Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius <hi>extolled, as the famous Biſhops of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:105495:60"/>
and third Age; but to write as methodical, weighty, pious Tractates, as any that were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by men, that neither con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed with the Apoſtles, nor had been bred up in Phloſophy; no, not excepting</hi> Clemens Romanus <hi>himſelf,</hi> Ignatius, Irenaeus, Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian, Macarius, Ephrem Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, Iſidor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And as of Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Writing by the Spirit, ſo</p>
               <p n="4">4. Praying by the Spirit, I mean the extemporate faculty of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to make this (as ſome do) the infallible Mark or Sign, Work or Effect, of Gods Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, is that many call Phanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm: God doth undoubtedly vouchſafe to devout and pious minds, the ſpecial Aſſiſtance of his Spirit, which perhaps may be properly enough called pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the Spirit: But then this muſt be placed not in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporate
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:105495:61"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:105495:61"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:105495:62"/>
Faculty, not in vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lubility of Tongue, or quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Fancy, variety of Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or readineſs of Expreſſion; but in ſuch devout affections, and ſuch reverent Apprehenſions of Gods Majeſty, as do beſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the moſt ſolemn acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of him, and as are apteſt to incite Faith, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and a Holy Fear and Love of God; this, if any thing, is Praying by the Spirit; and not the extem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate Faculty, that is ſo far from being the diſtinguiſhing Work of Gods Spirit, that the vileſt Profligates may have it; and therefore to aſcribe it to the Spirit of God, as ſuch a Work, is properly called Phanaticiſm: And of this there is this remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Inſtance to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:105495:62"/>At St. <hi>Ives,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Counterm.</hi> ch. 7. p. 49.</note> in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Huntington,</hi> in the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of many Perſons now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, there was a Woman moſt Zealouſly devoted to the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Party, then called <hi>Profeſſors,</hi> or <hi>Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans;</hi> a conſtant frequenter She was of Religious Meetings, whereby She became ſo Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, eſpecially in this gift of Prayer, that ſhe was ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally admired, and looked upon as a firſt-rate Saint: The noiſe of her Fame, and the boaſts of her Party, brought many Neighbouring Miniſters of the Adjacent Counties of <hi>Cambridge</hi> and <hi>Huntington,</hi> to hear her Pray; which She did in that Ecſtatick manner, that they never parted from her with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exceſs of Admiration. After ſome time, She went
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:105495:63"/>
(with many others) into <hi>New England,</hi> for Liberty of Conſcience; where She lived for ſome time in greateſt eſteem; but the Devil ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Her a Shame, and She owed him a Soul; She was at laſt Suſpected and Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of being a Witch, was brought to her Tryal, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed her Guilt, and that her Contract with the Devil was, That in lieu of her Soul, which ſhe had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to him, he ſhould aſſiſt her with the gift of <hi>Extempore</hi>-Prayer; after which Confeſſion, Sentence paſſed upon her, and ſhe was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly executed for an abominable Witch. Many the like Inſtances of this, there are in a late Book, called <hi>Ravillack Redivivus.</hi> Now ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we muſt ſay, That the Devil has Power of diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:105495:63"/>
of the gifts of Gods Spirit (which is Blaſphemy) or that this Extemporate way of praying, is no infallible ſign of Gods Spirit; and therefore, that it is <hi>Phanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm</hi> to aſcribe it to him: In a word, as Miracles ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo did the gift of inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Prayer; and ever ſince, has the Church Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped God by allowed Forms, or Liturgies; not only in the <hi>Bohemian,</hi> and <hi>Lutheran</hi> Churches, but in the <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian</hi> Churches of <hi>Geneva, France, Holland,</hi> &amp;c. and that not only allowed, but adviſed by Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; till of late, ſome Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits in Maſquerade, firſt ſet up the way of Extemporary Prayer on purpoſe to break good Order in the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Churches, and eſpecially, here in <hi>England;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Foxes and Firebrands.</note> as is lately made
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:105495:64"/>
evident beyond all reach of ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, by a good credible Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor.</p>
               <p n="5">5. 'Tis rank Phanaticiſm to reſiſt Lawful Authority on pretence of Religion; or to pretend Conſcience for Diſobedience to Magiſtrates; hereby God has been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled to as barbarous Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacres, and as horrid Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions, as ever were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; and this ſort of men are ſo far Phanatick, as they intitle God to ſelf-inconſiſtency, in oppoſing his Will to his Will, and his Word to his Word; by pretending his Authority for Diſobedience to his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners: For Conſcience is no leſs than a Divine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and therefore not to be pretended without, much leſs againſt a Divine
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:105495:64"/>
Law. The pretence of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is, that we are afraid to diſpleaſe God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore chuſe rather to diſpleaſe men; but if we diſpleaſe men to pleaſe God, where God has forbid that Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, or Diſobeying of men, <hi>[as in the caſe of Diſobedence to Magiſtrates in things not ſinful]</hi> in that caſe, the pleaſing of God is but pretended, and that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is but Fanaticiſm; it being Diſobedience on the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Conſcience, or Duty to God, where there is no Word or Law of God commanding it.</p>
               <p>'Tis eternally true, That a Conſcience informed, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by a Divine Law, ought not to ſtoop to the greateſt Prince; That the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of God is to be
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:105495:65"/>
oppoſed to the greateſt Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er upon Earth; And that all the Powers in the World, cannot deliver us from the Obligation of CONSCIENCE, that is, when it has Gods Law for its Rule: But where that is wanting, it is not properly Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but Humour and Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; and pretending that Law, and that Divine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, when we have it not, is plain intituling Gods Majeſty, not meerly to Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour and Fancy, but to that damnable Sin of Diſobedience, which is properly called Phana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiſm.</p>
               <p>This Account have I given, not to juſtifie that ill pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of giving odious Names to any Party; but meerly to inſtruct the Vulgar Reader a little in that great evil of
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:105495:65"/>
Schiſm and Faction, which is ſo little diſcerned by ſuch, and leſs made Conſcience of by moſt.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:105495:66"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105495:66"/>
            <head>Remarks on Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi>'s Plea for Moderation.</head>
            <p>THE Arch-Pagan <hi>Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> having wrote a moſt Peſtilent Book againſt Chriſtianity, gave it this ſpecious Title, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And in imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him, it was that<note n="*" place="margin">Not <hi>Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go</hi> Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat.</note> 
               <hi>Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> an <hi>Egyptian</hi> Governour, wrote two Books to prove the Scriptures guilty of Falſhood and Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: The Apoſtles to have been Cheats and Impoſtors: The Miracles of Chriſt to have been the Effect of Magick, and not comparable to thoſe of <hi>Apollonius Tyanaeus:</hi> Yet this helliſh Book, he did Intitle, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. As tho
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:105495:67"/>
its damnable Errors had been Divine Truths, and not againſt, but for the Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>In like manner Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi> [a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſt Miniſter, who declares him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſatisfied in the lawfulneſs of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing required in the Church of <hi>England</hi>] in imitation of Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>'s <hi>Pleas for Peace,</hi> has pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed a Book which he calls, <hi>A Plea for Moderation to'ards Diſſenters,</hi> which is indeed ſuch a Plea for Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſneſs and Confuſion, ſuch a piece of Hypocriſie and Church-Treachery, and ſuch a perfect Satyr upon the Government, as deſerves a worſe <hi>Shammatha</hi> than what is <hi>ipſo facto</hi> pronounced againſt him in the Sixth Canon, for impugning the Rites and Ceremonies of the Church: Or at leaſt, 'tis a Plea for ſuch Moderation <hi>as (Dr.</hi> Taylor <note n="‖" place="margin">Ductor Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>ſays) has ſomething of Craft in it, but little of Ingenuity; that may ſerve the ends of outward Charity, or Phantaſtick Concord, but not of Truth and Holineſs: Moderation</hi> (ſaies
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105495:67"/>
Biſhop <hi>Lany) cannot be but between two Extreams;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sermon on</hi> 1 Theſ. 4.11.</note> 
               <hi>and what Extreams are there in a ſetled Church (as in</hi> England) <hi>unleſs the Church be one Extream, and the Schiſmatick the other</hi> (ſaies the Biſhop)? But to ſhew further the vanity and empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his promiſing Title, if you take the word <hi>Moderation</hi> in its forenſick and primary Acceptation, for that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or gentleneſs which is placed in relaxing the Rigour of the Laws, when they preſs too hard upon Criminals; I do undertake in theſe following Lines to make it evident, That the Moderation of our Church and Church-Rulers is ſuch, that it is plain want of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration to queſtion their Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and that they are utterly loſt to all Moderation, who attempt ſuch Pleas in that behalf.</p>
            <p>If you take the word Moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in its Scripture-Acceptation, it is no more than Meekneſs under Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, Perſecutions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the Context of that one,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105495:68"/>
and only place where it is uſed in Scripture, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Let your Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration,</hi> or (as the <hi>Geneva</hi> Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation] let your Patient mind <hi>be known unto all men, q. d.</hi> however immoderate your Perſecutors are, let your Moderation, Meekneſs and Patience, be known to all men, not only Fellow-Sufferers, but your Enemies and Perſecutors. Shewing plainly, that the word <hi>Moderation</hi> in Scripture-Acceptation, is accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modable to none but a ſuffering or perſecuted Party. Which makes it <hi>a contradictio in adjecto,</hi> to call this Book <hi>a Plea for Moderation to'ards Diſſenters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as the Title, ſo the Book, <hi>Dignum patellâ operculum:</hi> For there's ſcarce a Paragraph in it not fairly reducible to one of theſe Heads.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Fraudulent Pleas for Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with Diſſenters in the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſance or Non-impoſal of Church Ceremonies.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:105495:68"/>2. For Indulgence to'ards them in relaxing the Rigour of the Laws.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Scandalous Reflections.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Impertinent Jorgon.</p>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Remarks on Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi>'s Plea concerning Church-Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</head>
               <p>TO ſee how in this he doth in <hi>limine impingere,</hi> He begins his Book with this Fraudulent Inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation concerning them. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Rites and Ceremonies,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 1. 4. 8. 18. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>and Zeal about them; a Stratagem of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils Invention, whereby to hinder the Progreſs of true Chriſtianity; hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Devices, old Rites and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, trifling and frivolous Things;</hi> with much more to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
               <p>How far he hath hereby incurr'd the Penalty annex'd to violation of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105495:69"/>
the 6th Canon, which ſaies of the Impugners of the Rites and Ceremonies of the Church of <hi>England, Let them be excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated: And of the</hi> 10th <hi>Canon, which calls them maintainers of Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks who ſhall dare to publiſh that any ſeparated Church has of long time groaned under the burden of certain grievances impoſed upon it,</hi> [ſpeaking before of Gods Worſhip in the Church of <hi>England,] and that whoſoever ſhall preſume ſo to do, ſhall be excommunicated, and not reſtored till they repent and publickly revoke ſuch their wicked error.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And of the Act for Uniformity, 1. Q <hi>Eliz.</hi> which ſaies, <hi>If any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare or ſpeak any thing in deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Common-Prayer, or</hi> any thing therein contained — <hi>he ſhall loſe and forfeit for his firſt Offence, the profit of all his ſpiritual Benefices or Promotions for one whole year, and ſuffer Impriſonment for ſix Months without Bail or Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe; and for the ſecond Offence ſhall
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105495:69"/>
be impriſon'd one whole year, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of all his ſpiritual Promoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:</hi> How far he has incurr'd this Penalty, let others judg; that which I remark is in theſe following par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. His inſinuateing concerning the Church Ceremonies,<note place="margin">P. 4. 20.</note> as <hi>humane Devices, and humane Inventions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereas the Church of <hi>England</hi> has retain'd but one Ritual or Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, that is not of Divine Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and Apoſtolick practice (as Biſhop <hi>Taylor</hi> has obſerved) and that is the Croſs at Baptiſm,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ductor Dubit.</hi> lib. 3. c. 4.</note> which is a compliance with the practice of all Ancient Churches: The Church has but this one Ceremony of its own appointment; for the Ring in Marriage is the Symbol of a Civil and religious Contract, a Pledge and Cuſtom of the Nation, not of the Religion. As for other Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, they are but Determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of time, place, and manner of Duty, and ſerve for no other pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes then ſignifications for Order
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105495:70"/>
and Decency: For which (ſaies he) there is an Apoſtolical precept, and a Natural reaſon, and an evident neceſſity, or great convenience.</p>
               <p>And notwithſtanding the uſe of this ſign in Baptiſm has ever been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with the greateſt Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Care and Cautions againſt all Popiſh Superſtition and Error (as the 30th Canon ſhews.) And not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the reverend eſteem that the Primitive Church had of it, in ſo much (ſaies that Canon) <hi>That if any oppoſed it, they would certainly have been cenſured not only as Enemies of the name of the Croſs, but of the Merits of Chriſt:</hi> And notwithſtanding the Conceſſions of the moſt Eminent Nonconformiſts granting the lawfulneſs of its uſe:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Baxter <hi>Chriſt. Direct.</hi> Q. 113.</note> Yet doth this Pleader give it as ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous and abſur'd a name as any could be thought of, calling it in plain <hi>Engliſh, contradictio in adjecto,</hi> and this on no other then this ſilly account;<note place="margin">P. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>The ill Opinions that it begets in the minds of the Ignorant,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105495:70"/>
as tho it were indiſpenſibly neceſſary, and a part of the Ordinance of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, and as tho private Baptiſm without the Croſs is not true ſound Baptiſm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this there is this ſufficient An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer in the 30th Canon.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the abuſe of a thing doth not take away the lawful uſe of it (or make the uſe of it unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful) which is the more regardable, becauſe ſpoken as the Church's ſenſe in ſpecial reference to the Croſs in Baptiſm.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſame Canon ſaies, That the uſe of this ſign was ever accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with ſufficient Cautions and Exceptions againſt Superſtition and Error:<note place="margin">Common-Prayer Book Preface of Church Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</note> And the Church has elſewhere fully declared againſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of any ſuch Ceremonies as are like to be abuſed to Superſtition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Tho this Propoſition <hi>[private Baptiſm is no true ſound Baptiſm]</hi> ſeem ſomewhat contradictory, yet to ſhew that it is nothing ſo, to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105495:71"/>
make it what Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi> calls it <hi>contradictio in adjecto;</hi> there muſt be <hi>incompoſſibilitas terminorum:</hi> The <hi>Adjecta</hi> or <hi>Termini</hi> here, are <hi>[pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, ſound];</hi> and who can appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend any incompoſſibility or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnancy in thoſe terms, as they relate to Baptiſm? Beſides, if by ſound Baptiſm may be meant com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat and perfect Baptiſm; then the Rubrick (and Directory alſo) doth ſcarce allow of private Baptiſm as ſound Baptiſm, except in the caſe of dying Infants. And ſince he ſpeaks of the Ignorant only, why may not ſuch take ſound Baptiſm in that Senſe? So that in plain his hinting the Croſs at Baptiſm by that odious name, is ſuch a thick piece of Error as may be felt, and (in a Conformiſt) ſuch a thin piece of Hypocriſie, as the weakeſt eye may ſee through; and ten times worſe then Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s whimſey in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioning whether we do not make the Croſs at Baptiſm <hi>A new Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Covenant of Grace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Firſt Plea for Peace.</note> which
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105495:71"/>
no one part of the Definition of a Sacrament can be made to agree with. He proceeds againſt the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of Ceremonies in general, thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our Saviour lays no ſtreſs on any thing, but real practical Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Obedience to lawful Authority in things indifferent, is real practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Religion, and Inconformity or Diſobedience to lawful Authority, is damnable Sin.</p>
               <p>He adds,<note place="margin">Page 9.</note> 
                  <hi>The Apoſtles upon mature Deliberation— would lay no more on the Diſciples, then what was then neceſſary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. No more do the Apoſtles and Governours of our Church now. But to ſhew how impertinently this is urged,</p>
               <p n="2">2. 'Tis evident by the Context, that thoſe words of the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> relate particularly to Circumciſion,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 15.</note> which was not a <hi>Jewiſh</hi> ceremony, but a <hi>Jewiſh</hi> ſacrament of divine inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and alteration both, and therefore nothing to our purpoſe; and yet St.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105495:72"/>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> circumciſed <hi>Timothy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 16.3.</note> meerly in conformity to the <hi>Jews:</hi> And at that ſame Council, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. when the Apoſtles had declared againſt Circumciſion, at the ſame time (as in the next verſe) they declared for the <hi>Gentiles</hi> abſtaining from things ſtrangled, and from Blood, which there was no Law of God for oblige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Gentiles</hi> to, but what the Apoſtles enjoined them meerly on the account of Peace and Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to the Church National of the <hi>Jews</hi> they lived in, according to the grand Exemplar Chriſt his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying all along with the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church in their Rites and Cuſtoms, obſerving their Feaſts, and making his own Inſtitutions of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> and the <hi>Lord Supper</hi> as agreeable to their Cuſtoms as was poſſible. And ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his example all a long, the Apoſtles not like inflexible ſtarch't Phariſees, but like humble com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſant Chriſtians, <hi>became all things to all, to the</hi> Jews <hi>as</hi> Jews, <hi>and to thoſe without the Law, as without the Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:105495:72"/>In the next place he ſtarts this Queſtion,<note place="margin">Page 9.</note> as that which he ſaies ſome do much inſiſt upon; <hi>Whether the Apoſtles had not power to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine indifferent Ceremonies, ſo as to oblige the Church in her ſeveral Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations to the uſe of ſome, and to forbear the uſe of all others? He reſolves it thus, They never made uſe of their power, that we read of,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Page 10.</note> 
                  <hi>about theſe indifferent and unneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was not neceſſary they ſhould; the general Rule and Reaſon being ſufficient to ſecure the Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any capital Miſtake. That the Apoſtles never obliged the Church to the uſe of ſome Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, or the difuſe of others, ſo as to oblige all after-times to any particular form of Rituals, is certain; And alſo, that they gave only gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Directions, but left it to the Power and Prudence of Church-Rulers to determine of Particulars, as the various Conditions of People, Time and Place ſhould reſpectively
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105495:73"/>
require; This is evident from hence, that the Apoſtles inſtituted ſeveral things in the Primitive Churches, which were in after-times to be uſed or diſuſed, as Church-Rulers ſhould think fit. For inſtance, the <hi>Agapae,</hi> or Love-feaſts, the holy Kiſs, the order of <hi>Deaconneſſes,</hi> and ſeveral other things, which are now utterly diſuſed and laid aſide, tho of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Inſtitution. Nor doth any man ſcruple the Diſuſe or Abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them; which is a palpable evidence, that the Apoſtles never deſigned a certain form of Rituals to all after-ages, but left it to the Prudence and Power of Church-Rulers to appoint as they ſee fit. And thus Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> himſelf,<note place="margin">Calv. Inſt. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 10.30.</note> In externa diſciplina &amp; Ceremoniis non voluit Chriſtus, <hi>&amp;c. Chriſt would not preſcribe ſingularly and ſpecially concerning external Diſcipline and Ceremonies, becauſe he foreſaw theſe things were to depend on the occaſions and opportunities of times, and ought to be accommodated to the Edification
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105495:73"/>
of the Church, according to the different diſpoſition and cuſtom of Times and Countries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He adds,<note place="margin">Page 10.</note> 
                  <hi>I think it will be very difficult for any man to make it appear, that for ſome hundreds of years after the Apoſtles, the Orthodox Chriſtian Church did ever require any more then common Chriſtianity, as a term or condition of Church Communion, or that any Ceremony was for ſo long a time impoſed on the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Orthodox Chriſtian Church did require it as the term or conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Church-Communion, That the lapſed Penitents ſhould perform the five ſeveral Stages of Penance in ſuch Poſture and Geſture as the Church impoſed, and no other; wherefore one ſort of Penitents were called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> the <hi>Proſtrate,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were to perform their Penance in the Geſture of Proſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and no other. They wore cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Marks of Penance about them, with ſeveral other Ceremonies that I could name, which were <hi>impoſed</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:105495:74"/>
on them as terms of Church-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ignatius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Antioch</hi> and Martyr, who lived in the Apoſtles times,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Socr. Hiſt.</hi> l. 6. c. 8.</note> is reported by <hi>Socrates</hi> to have heard in a Viſion the Angels cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brating the Praiſes of God in Alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Hymns; and in Imitation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of appointed the ceremonious way of <hi>Antiphones,</hi> or reſponſal Hymns in the Church of <hi>Antioch,</hi> which was immediately appointed in (or impoſed on) moſt Chriſtian Churches in the World. The Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony or Order of reading the two Leſſons after the Pſalms, is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the Apoſtolick Canons,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ap. Can.</hi> lib. 2. can. 57.</note> as a thing decreed or appointed (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joined or impoſed) which <hi>Caſſianus</hi> mentions as the Ancient cuſtom of all the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Churches,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Caſſian.</hi> l. 2. c. 4.</note> which he ſaies was not taught by men, but by the Miniſtry of Angels from Heaven.<note place="margin">Epipha. <hi>adv.</hi> Aerians.</note> 
                  <hi>Epiphanius</hi> calls the <hi>Aeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> the moſt Brainſick Hereticks that ever were, for holding that Biſhops and Presbyters were all one,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105495:74"/>
and that they were not bound to keep Lent, and the Holy week, as the <hi>Laws of the Holy Church re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired: Sozomen</hi> ſpeaks of ſtanding up at the Goſpel,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hiſtory</hi> lib. 7. <hi>c.</hi> 19.</note> as a thing very anciently and univerſally impoſed: He ſaies it was a new Faſhion in <hi>Alexandria,</hi> that the Biſhop did not riſe up, when the Goſpel was read, and that he never heard of the like elſewhere.</p>
               <p>And the Council of <hi>Toleta</hi> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Con.</hi> 11. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> That all Governours of Churches, and their People, ſhould obſerve the ſame Rites and Order of Service, which they knew to be appointed in the Metropolitan See. In the early days of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> who lived near the Apoſtles times, there was diſtinction of Garments, bowing to'ard the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable other Ceremonies; and among the reſt, there's no queſtion to be made of what Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi> has ſuch a ſpight at, the Croſs at Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, ſince the Church ſaies (Canon 30.) that it was uſed in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105495:75"/>
and Apoſtolical Churches with one conſent. All which Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies <hi>Tertullian</hi> calls<note n="*" place="margin">Harum &amp; aliarum ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi Diſciplinarum ſi legem expoſtules Scripturarum, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venies nullam; ſed traditio eſt auctrix, conſuetudo conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatrix, &amp; fides obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix.</note> 
                  <hi>Diſciplines,</hi> which implies that they were impoſed; yet there was then no ſuch thing as ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pling of Ceremonies, but obedience active and paſſive, even to <hi>Pagan</hi> Governours; and conformity to Chriſtian Church-Orders, was a Characteriſtical mark of primitive Chriſtianity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whatever the Pleaders name be, to ſhew that his Temper is daring; he tells us,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>p.</hi> 11, 12.</note> 
                  <hi>He dares affirm, That if the Rights and Ceremonies now in uſe, in the Church of</hi> England, <hi>ſhould be alter'd, ſome changed, and ſome wholly laid aſide, by the ſame Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity that did at firſt injoin them, the Church of</hi> England <hi>would ſtill be as impregnable a Bulwark againſt Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, as now ſhe is; and I am fully ſatisfied</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>there is no man will deny this, unleſs he be either a
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105495:75"/>
real</hi> Papiſt, <hi>or an</hi> ignorant ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Fool.</p>
               <p>The King, Parliaments, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations have denyed it; and I am fully ſatisfied they muſt and will deny it on theſe accounts following.</p>
               <p n="1">1. On the account of the great danger that univerſal Obſervation and Experience have found to be in ſuch Innovation as he pleads for, in altering the Conſtitutions of a Church <hi>[that have heen com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and ſetled by wiſe men and Chriſtian Martyrs, reverenced and admired by others, incorporated into the Laws of the Land, rivetted by Cuſtom and long Preſcription]</hi> for the ſake of ſuch novel Notions, and inconſiſtent Alterations, as no diſſenting Party could ever yet agree in, and ſuch as is inſeparably twiſted with ſeditious and penici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Alterations in the State. It being much more true of <hi>England,</hi> what <hi>Optatus</hi> ſaid of <hi>Milevis, Res publica non eſt in eccleſia, ſed eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia in republica;</hi> and therefore, that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105495:76"/>
the Church being contained in a Civil Society, muſt conform its ſelf (in externals) to that which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains it, for Safety and Preſervation.</p>
               <p>Which made King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt call ſuch Alteration,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</note> 
                  <hi>The old leaven of Innovation, under the mask of Reformation, which in his two laſt Predeceſſors days, heaved at, and threatned both Prince and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> They firſt deſired Alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of him, and then obtruded it on him with the point of their Swords; with ſuch a truſting to their <hi>Moderation,</hi> which he there calls <hi>abandoning his own Diſcretion;</hi> and ſhews throughout, that they who began with nothing elſe but ſuch deſires of <hi>Moderation</hi> and <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration</hi> (as Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi> Pleads for) ceaſed in nothing elſe but utter Subverſion and Diſſolution: And Arch-Biſhop <hi>Bramhall</hi> (whom Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> truly calls,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lett. to</hi> Mr. Militier.</note> that clear-headed Metropolitan) teaches, <hi>That it is a rule in prudence, not to alter (no not) an ill cuſtom, when it is well ſetled.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105495:76"/>
Needleſs Alteration doth ſo diminiſh the venerable eſteem of Religion, and leſſen the credit of ancient Truths; break Ice in one place</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>and it will crack in another.</hi> And twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years ſmart Experience of the ill conſequences of giving way to ſuch fraudulent Pleas for <hi>Moderation,</hi> and little Alterations, hath made it neceſſary to <hi>deny</hi> [without being <hi>real Papiſt, or ſuperſtitious Fool</hi>] that ſuch Alteration ſhould be made in conſideration of the Church of <hi>Englands</hi> being as great a Bulwark againſt Popery in the Alteration, as without it; eſpecially conſidering,</p>
               <p n="2">2. The great advantage it would give the Papiſts; the ill Reflection it would make on the Proteſtant Reformers; and the Scandal it would caſt upon the Proteſtant Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to ſee men make no difference between intolerable Superſtitions, and innocent Rites and Ceremonies; we have inſtance of this in Biſhop <hi>Hooper</hi>'s ſcrupling the Epiſcopal Veſtments, of which ſaid <hi>Peter
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105495:77"/>
Martyr, Such needleſs ſcrupuloſity will be a great hinderance to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; and 'tis certain, that there was ſcarce any thing gave ſo great check to the Reformation, in</hi> France <hi>eſpecially, among moderate and learned men, as the putting no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between the Corruptions of Popery, and the innocent cuſtoms of the Ancient Church: For when thoſe of</hi> France, <hi>that were inclined to the Reformation, ſaw that the Reformers oppoſed the undoubted Practices of Antiquity, equally with the Popiſh Corruptions; they caſt them off, as men guilty of an unreaſonable humour of Innovation.</hi> And ſo at this day, when men contend about things indifferent, as tho unlawful, and would have ſuch Ceremonies as are of truly Primitive, and for the moſt part<note n="‖" place="margin">Can. 30.</note> Apoſtolical Practice, equally diſuſed as things perfectly Superſtitious, the vulgar Papiſts (at leaſt) that cannot diſtinguiſh, muſt conclude, that we alter or aboliſh ſuch innocent Ceremonies as
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105495:77"/>
Standing, Kneeling, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> on the ſame grounds as we do the reſt of their deteſtable Corruptions; and ſo by ſeeing our unwarrantableneſs in reforming from thoſe innocent Ceremonies, are eaſily (if not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily) induced to believe the unwarrantableneſs of our departing from the whole Maſs of Popery; eſpecially conſidering, that it is the buſineſs of their Teachers to inſtruct them in this, That we reform from both, on the ſame grounds; and what can this tend to, but to harden Papiſts, and ſcandalize Proteſtants, and ſo endanger the Reformed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion?</p>
               <p>And for theſe, and perhaps many more weighty Reaſons than Mr. <hi>Bolde,</hi> or my ſelf can apprehend, Our Rulers have thought fit, in point of Moderation, to retain the Ceremonies now in uſe, in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Enthuſiaſtick Innovation on the one hand, and Popiſh Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on the other hand. And therefore Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi> doth very ill
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:105495:78"/>
in calling every one a <hi>real Papiſt, or ſuperſtitious Fool,</hi> that will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the Alteration or Abolition of our Church-Ceremonies, on the ſuppoſal of the Church of <hi>England</hi>'s being as great a Bulwark againſt Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery in the Alteration, as without it; I ſay, he doth very ill to call every ſuch one, by ſuch odious Names; eſpecially conſidering, that the King and Parliaments are moſt immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately concerned in it.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi> having told us in the following lines, of the fruit and effect of Impoſitions, and the want of making ſome Conceſſions and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batements for the ſake of thoſe that are yet unſatisfied; adds more particularly, that <hi>there are yet two dreadful events which have followed theſe Impoſitions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Many worthy, pious, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe every way qualified Perſons, have been hinder'd from either en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering into, or continuing in the Lords Vineyard to labour and work there.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:105495:78"/>1. They hinder themſelves: All that the Law doth, is but to hold forth one common Rule, which Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi> cannot deny, but that they may conform to without Sin.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There are as many worthy, and well qualified men of the Churches Communion, as there are Diſſenters, who are yet deſtitute expectants of being called into the Vineyard: I heard a Reverend Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late but t'other day ſpeaking of an account which the Arch-Biſhop ſaid was lately given in to him, of above two thouſand ſuch in <hi>England:</hi> And tho it cannot be denied, but among the Diſſenters, there are many who Preach well; yet take a great part of thoſe who are moſt admired by the Vulgar, and you will find, that the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of their Preaching lies chiefly in a faculty they have of moving a Paſſion; either by tranſporting or confounding the Imagination with ſome Myſtical Repreſentations, or
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105495:79"/>
by thundering into mens ears the moſt formidable or dreadful Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; or by ſmiling out now and then a ſoft Similitude, or a chiming Cadency, a curled Metaphor, or ſome ſuch <hi>Pſeudotrope;</hi> and with inſinuating Harmony of voice and geſture, tickle the Soul up into the Ear of the weakeſt Sex eſpecially, and thoſe of ſhallow Judgment and warm Affection; but are more like to provoke the Scorn and Laughter of a ſturdy Profligate, than to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince his Judgment, or work upon his heart.</p>
               <p>But among the conforming Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, the buſineſs in preaching, is not to ſtand fluttering in myſtical Nonſence, and <hi>Stentorian</hi> Noiſe; but to deliver themſelves gravely and conſiderately, rationally and judiciouſly, calmly and modeſtly; to enlighten the Hearers minds with ſuch ſubſtantial and nervous Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe, as is fitted to ſtop the mouths of Gainſayers, that they ſhall not be able to reſiſt that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105495:79"/>
that Spirit and Power of Reaſon and Religon with which they ſpeak; And of theſe, ſince God has ſpoke the word, great is the company, more by ſome hundreds than the Vineyard will hold: And therefore 'tis not to be believed that the hindering Diſſenters on ſuch dangerous and unreaſonable terms on which they would come into the Vineyard, is ſuch a dreadful event or effect of Impoſitions, as Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi> ſpeaks of; eſpecially conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering (as has been ſhewn) that the hindrance is of themſelves.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Another dreadful event or effect of Impoſition, that he inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in, is this,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 12.</note> 
                  <hi>The conſtant impoſed uſe of theſe things has almoſt una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidably begot in the minds of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant People, a belief, that they are indiſpenſably neceſſary, and undoubted parts of thoſe Ordinances to which they are annexed,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The 30 Canon yeilds ſufficient Anſwer to this, in theſe two parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:105495:80"/>1. That the abuſe of a thing, doth not take away the uſe of it.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">Comm. Prayer Preface, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</note>2. The Church has poſitively declared againſt the retaining any Ceremony in uſe, which may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed to Superſtition.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Why may not the ignorant People, as well believe them indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſably neceſſary to be uſed, as indiſpenſably neceſſary to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſed? the Superſtition of the one is juſt as much as the Superſtition of the other. But,</p>
               <p n="4">4. I know no Error in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of <hi>Ceremonies being indiſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly neceſſary, and undoubted parts of the Ordinances they are annexed to.</hi> Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> himſelf ſeems to be of that belief; when he calls thoſe Inſtitutions, which are founded in Scripture,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Inſtit.</hi> lib. 4. c. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>prorſus divinas,</hi> altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Divine; Divine, becauſe a part of that decency, the care and obſervation whereof is commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to us in thoſe words, <hi>let all things be done decently and in order;</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:105495:80"/>
but humane, ſo far as they are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated by men to ſome circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Perſon, Time, or Place.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi> proceeds next to play the Emperick, in preſcribing to the body-politick, Church and State: The diſeaſe is, <hi>falling out and quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling about old Rights and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,</hi> p. 8. &amp; paſſim; <hi>and he has no remedy for this; but the Churches yeilding</hi> [to its Enemies] <hi>in altering ſome, and wholly laying aſide other of her Ceremonies,</hi> p. 11. <hi>That abatements might be made to Diſſenters,</hi> p. 12. <hi>who are to be Proſelyted by the Churches condeſcending and yielding,</hi> p. 19. And the like throughout his Book, like a Vein through his Body; and thus he preſcribes to Parliaments in chief, <hi>p.</hi> 25.</p>
               <p>Can any thing be more <hi>Baxteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> than ſuch arrogant preſcribing to Princes and Parliaments? Or is not this, as if he had ſaid, that the makers of the Law muſt concede to the Subjects of the Law? that Laws and Law-makers, both, muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105495:81"/>
to Nonconformity? that Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments and Synods, <hi>[thoſe moſt auguſt and venerable Aſſemblies in the World]</hi> muſt ſtoop to Scepticks and Innovators? Authority and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity to Novelty and Bigotry? Primitive practice to innovating humour? and Majeſty its ſelf to peeviſh, and turbulent, and endleſs Scrupuloſity? And all this, ſaies Mr. <hi>Bolde, to ſatisfie ſome that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied,</hi> i.e. (as ſome love to ſpeak) unſatisfied in Conſcience, profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly calling by that ſacred Name of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> what men of greateſt Learning, ſtricteſt Piety and Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and moſt comfortable Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, have called <hi>ſturdineſs of Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> in ſome, weakneſs and unſetled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Judgment in others, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a meer fear of doing what God commands, for fear of Sin: But pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuant to his Plea for the Churches yielding to its Enemies in the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration and Abolition of Church-Ceremonies, He tells this dull Story from <hi>Beza,</hi> that was a ſworn Enemy to Epiſcopacy:</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:105495:81"/>
                  <hi>A Noble-man having finiſh'd the building of his houſe, ſuffer'd a great Stone to lie before the houſe, which he had no occaſion for; the People ſtumbling at it in the dark, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained; the Noble man would not ſuffer the Stone to be took away, but order'd a Lanthorn to be hung out over it; this not ſecuring the People from the inconveniences of it, the Noble-man was at laſt intreated to remove the Stone and Lanthern both:</hi> But whether he did remove them or no, that Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi> keeps to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
               <p>Without any remark on the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinence of this dull Story,<note place="margin">Serious and compaſſionate Enquiry, <hi>p. 10.</hi>
                  </note> I ſhall be ſo civil to Mr. <hi>Bolde,</hi> as to return it from a more conſiderable Author than <hi>Beza,</hi> thus:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Apelles</hi> to deride the conceited folly of the Age, expoſes to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick view, a Maſter-piece of his Work, and as it uſually happens (by the encouragement of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, <hi>Facile eſt inventis adhere</hi>) every body pretends to skill in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:105495:82"/>
ſcarce any paſſed by, but paſſed their Verdict on the Picture, all generally commend it; yet to give ſome inſtance of their skill, every one finds ſome fault or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; one would have had more ſhade, another leſs; one commends the Eye, but blames the Lip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The cunning Artiſt obſerves all, but ſays nothing; and ſtill as any Paſſenger gave his Verdict, he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters the Picture accordingly; the reſult was this, by its Alteration and Reformation, it became ſuch Abomination of Deformation, ſuch a horrid monſtrous Piece, that the very Reformers themſelves won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd at its Uglineſs. <hi>Apelles</hi> to right himſelf, produces another piece of the ſame Art and Beauty which he had hitherto kept up by him, and ſo had eſcaped their cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; with this he upbraids them thus, <hi>Hanc ego faci iſtam populus:</hi> This I made, the t'other is a Devil of your own making.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:105495:82"/>Now not to be ſo abrupt as Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi> was, as to run from my Story without any Application. Chriſtian Religion was by Wiſe and Holy men, our Reformers, diveſted of thoſe meretricious and gaudy Accoutrements, that the Papiſts had dreſt her up with, and habited her according to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive ſimplicity; but this (tho amiable of it ſelf) would not pleaſe every Body, every Sect or Party would have ſomething alter'd, which if it were allowed (the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of men are ſo contrary to one another, as well as to truth) the true lineaments of Chriſtianity would be loſt, and ſo our Religion have the ſame fate, that the poor Picture of <hi>Apelles</hi> had.</p>
               <p>But in pleading for Alteration of ſome Ceremonies, and laying others wholly aſide, Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi> proceeds to ſeven Arguments.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt is this, <hi>It is unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionably certain, that the cloſer any
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:105495:83"/>
Church doth keep, or the nearer ſhe approaches to the firſt Churches, in their ſimplicity and freedom from hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane inventions, the more juſtifiable ſhe will be;</hi> and ſo on</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Ceremonies we retain are ſo few, that if compared with the vaſt numbers uſed in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or in the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Chriſtian Churches in St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>'s time, they will appear to be <hi>vix quod Thebarum por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae,</hi> next to none in the compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Thoſe few Ceremonies we do retain, are according to the Practice and Simplicity of the firſt Churches. The 30th Canon ſaies, we depart from the Churches of <hi>Italy, France, Spain,</hi> and the like Churches, in thoſe points only, wherein they are fallen from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their ancient Integrity, and from the Apoſtolical Churches, which were their firſt Founders. Thus the Church of <hi>England</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:105495:83"/>
concerning Church Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies in general; and of the Croſs at Baptiſm in particular it ſays, we therein follow the primitive Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolic Churches. And</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is on no account more then agreement with the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Churches, that we retain the uſe of our few Ceremonies, and refuſe to yield to Diſſenters in altering ſome, and aboliſhing others; and therefore according to the Pleaders own Hypotheſis, our Church is moſt juſtifiable in ſo doing.</p>
               <p n="2">2. His Second Argument is this, <hi>That teaching that humane autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity has an unlimited power to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe any thing on the Church, which is not expreſly forbid in Scripture, may be of dangerous conſequence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The word <hi>(unlimited)</hi> is here impertinently foiſted in; for if hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane authority has power to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe on the Church what the Scripture doth not forbid, it muſt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:105495:84"/>
in that caſe have an unlimited power, becauſe nothing can limit it but the Scripture. If you take his aſſertion without the word <hi>(<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlimited)</hi> then it is that which Dr. <hi>Sanderſon</hi> called the very <hi>myſtery of Puritaniſm,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Serm. Preface.</note> and that which the very <hi>Proteſtant Reconciler</hi> doth contradict and confute;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 187.</note> and which is not only the very characteriſtick doctrine of the Diſſenters, but their chief fundamental, the very ground and foundation of their out-cries againſt ceremonies, as uncomman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded rites, humane inventions, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And whereas he ſays, this may be of <hi>dangerous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence,</hi> it's certain that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary is ſo; to teach that humane authority has not this power of impoſing on the Church, things not forbid in Scripture, but to demand a Scripture prohibition or precept, for every thing that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane authority impoſeth on the Church, is of moſt dangerous
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:105495:84"/>
conſequence, as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> has ſoundly proved, and ſhewed wherein, by an induction of about Twenty particulars;<note place="margin">Defence of the Principles of Love; p. <hi>97, 98, 99, 100, 101.</hi> &amp;c.</note> I ſhall no more than name but ſome of them.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It draws men into the dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous guilt of adding to the word of God, under pretence of defending its perfection. <hi>(He ſhews how)</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It ſorely prepares men for infidelity. <hi>(He ſhews how)</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. It alters the very definition of the Scripture, and makes it quite another thing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. It tends to caſt all-rational worſhip out of the Church, <hi>&amp;c</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. It will bring in all confuſion, inſtead of pure reaſonable wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. It will fright poor People from Scripture and Religion, and make us, our Doctrine, and Worſhip, ridiculous in the ſight of all the world, <hi>(as he ſhews at large.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. All poſſibility of Union a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Chriſtians and Churches,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:105495:85"/>
muſt periſh, if this error prevail, and be practiſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. It will have a confounding influence into all the affairs and buſineſs of our lives. Theſe and as many more Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> doth not barely name, (as I have done) but foundly proves to be the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of making Scripture a particular rule of circumſtantials in worſhip; or teaching, <hi>that humane authority has not power of impoſing on the Church things not forbid in Scripture.</hi> To all which, I add, That Sedition and Rebellion is not ſo apt to ariſe from any one Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Tenet whatſoever, as from this; for when men deny humane authority, the power of impoſing Church-ceremonies, for want of Scripture-precept or prohibition, they do on the ſame account call thoſe ceremonies <hi>Humane devices, uncommanded Rites, Popiſh and Superſtitious, &amp;c.</hi> and therefore (mark the conſequence) to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed; and if the Magiſtrate will
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:105495:85"/>
not reform it, the people muſt; and on this very principle have commenced the moſt barbarous and unnatural wars in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and other places: And therefore 'tis very diſingenuous in Mr. <hi>Bolde,</hi> not only to aſſert and vindicate this fundamental and moſt diſtinguiſhing principle of Diſſenters, but to accuſe its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary [a moſt undoubted truth] of <hi>Dangerous conſequences;</hi> when 'tis ſo apparent, that the dangerous conſequences are all on the other ſide.</p>
               <p>He proceeds on this head thus;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2.</note> 
                  <hi>It is not demonſtrably certain, that humane authority has power any further than to puniſh and reſtrain indecencies and diſorders in the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not to ſay whether this be not that ſpeaking againſt the Kings Sovereign Authority in cauſes Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical, which the 27th <hi>Can.</hi> cenſures.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:105495:86"/>1. It is demonſtrably certain, that humane authority had power to appoint Church-ceremonies, and to determine the circumſtantials in Religion. <hi>David</hi> alter'd ſome things, and inſtituted others, even in the Temple-Service, upon no other authority than humane. <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah</hi> on the ſame authority, and no other, broke the Brazen Serpent to pieces, though it was a ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical ceremony of Gods own inſtitution. He appointed the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites to kill the Paſſover, which by Gods appointment was to have been performed by the people themſelves: He preferr'd the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites to aſſiſt the Prieſts in killing the other Sacrifices, which they were never before admitted to: So that it is demonſtrably certain, <hi>That humane authority had once a power to determine the circumſtantials of Religion.</hi> Nor can Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi> tell when or how they came to be diveſted of it. But on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, when Chriſt ſaid, <hi>His King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:105495:86"/>
was not of this world,</hi> he plainly intimated, that he never intended to diveſt Governours of the authority they were poſſeſſed of.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It's demonſtrably certain, that the Scriptures do no where reſtrain the power of humane au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to puniſhing of diſorders or indecencies in the Church; when the Scripture commands, <hi>obey every ordinance of man,</hi> it ſuppoſeth in man, or humane au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, a power of making ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances; Church-ordinances not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted; and <hi>ubi lex non diſtinguit, non eſt diſtinguendum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It has been all along the practiſe of humane authority in all the reformed Churches, to inſtitute Church-diſcipline, and to impoſe it upon the people; and <hi>lex currit cum praxi:</hi> Thus <hi>Calvin</hi> himſelf writes to <hi>Farellus;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ep.</hi> 87.</note> 
                  <hi>To prevent the deſultory levity of thoſe who affect novelty, it always prevailed in the Church (which was decreed in ancient
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:105495:87"/>
Councils) That thoſe who would not be ſubject to the laws of common diſcipline, ſhould be diſmiſſed from their function. And</hi> Beza (<hi>on the life of</hi> Calvin) <hi>that ſubſcription to their Church-diſcipline was enjoined, not only Miniſters but people.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. That every Church National has power to inſtitute or appoint its Church-ceremonies, was one principal argument that our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Reformers made uſe of againſt the Papiſts, in altering our Religion from Popiſh to Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi>'s 3d Argument runs thus; <hi>The things we contend about are of ſuch a nature, they cannot bear ſo much weight as ſome lay upon them,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="1">1. How much the leſs the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are we contend about, ſo much the more is the ſin and ſhame of contentious diſobedience, and inconformity to them.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:105495:87"/>2. The more fit they are to be made a ſacrifice to peace; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when in obedience to that great Goſpel-precept of obedience to every <hi>humane</hi> ordinance, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. And ſince <hi>Mahomet</hi> muſt to the Mountain, or the Mountain to <hi>Mahomet,</hi> (as he ſpeaks) for ſhame let not Governours ſtoop to Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, antiquity to Novelty, and publick Authority, the higheſt on earth, to private fancy, the moſt humourſome and peeviſh: <hi>Since theſe things are not</hi> (ſays the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) <hi>matter of ſuch moment,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 24.</note> 
                  <hi>as moderate men ſhould lay out much of their zeal about.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He proceeds to ſhew how much miſchief men laying out too much zeal, and too much ſtreſs upon theſe things has occaſioned; he gives not ſo much as one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the miſchief; but inſtead of all inſtances, he cites Mr. <hi>Burgeſs</hi> in his Sermon before King <hi>James,</hi> for this Story.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:105495:88"/>
                  <hi>The Roman Emperour</hi> Auguſtus, <hi>in going to dine with a Senator of Rome, ſaw ſome company dragging a man after them, that made a horrid out-cry: The Emperour demanding the Reaſon; it was anſwered, their Maſter had condemned him to the Fiſh-ponds for breaking a Glaſs of great value: The Emperour ſtopp'd the Execution; and when he came to the Senators houſe, in expoſtula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the caſe with him, he asked him whether he had Glaſſes worth a mans life: That I have, ſays the Senator, Glaſſes that I value at the price of a Province. Let's ſee them (ſays the Emperor;) the Senator brought them: The Emperour broke them; with theſe words,</hi> Better all theſe periſh, than one man. My Author (ſays he) left it to his Majeſty to apply, and ſo do I to the Reader.</p>
               <p>And the Reader applies it thus; The <hi>Glaſſes</hi> are Church-ceremonies, the <hi>Senator</hi> is the Impoſer of them, the <hi>Emperour</hi> is the Oppoſer of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:105495:88"/>
them; the <hi>breaking</hi> of the Glaſſes, is the aboliſhing of the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies; <hi>rather than one man ſhould periſh,</hi> is rather than a peeviſh Party of Diſſenters ſhould be unſatisfied, who could never yet agree in the matter of their ſatisfaction, or in what alteration, condeſcenſion or conceſſion would ſatisfy them: But as in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time,<note n="*" place="margin">Dr. Ham. view of the Liturgy.</note> when to ſatisfy the clamours of Diſſenters againſt the Liturgy and Ceremonies, upon the impetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lord <hi>Burleigh,</hi> it was granted them, That an altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould be made, and a Claſſis of their own Party was appointed on purpoſe: But what alteration the firſt Claſſis made, was repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by a ſecond Claſſis of them, as more faulty than the old Liturgy; and that ſecond was reprehended by a third Claſſis, as moſt faulty of all: Whereby the Queen plainly ſaw that their cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours for alteration was for they knew not what, and that it was
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:105495:89"/>
impoſſible for them to agree in what they would have altered. The caſe is the ſame at this day; ſome diſſent on one account, others on another; ſome hold the whole Liturgy unlawful, others inexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient only; ſome hold it inexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient in ſome Offices, others in other; ſome ſtick at ſtanding or kneeling, others at nothing but the circumſtances of Baptiſm; ſome have accounted the <hi>Scotch</hi> Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant the great Mountain in the way; others ſcruple nothing but reordination:<note place="margin">Grand de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ate.</note> So that as a great Author of their own ſaid, 'Tis as eaſy to make a Coat for the Moon, as to reconcile them to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and make them agree in what alterations they would have. To what purpoſe then doth any Dogmatiſt trouble himſelf with Pleas and Interpoſals in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half. But to return Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi>'s Story of the <hi>Emperour</hi> and <hi>Senator</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Serious and compaſſionate Enquiry.</note> I will tell him one, from as good an Author as Mr. <hi>Burgeſs,</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:105495:89"/>
of the Emperor and Senator of <hi>Capua.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The People were all in a rage againſt the Senate, and would needs have them all depoſed; the Emperour <hi>Pacuvius Calavius</hi> ſhuts up the Senators all together, and claps a Guard upon them, and then comes to the People and tells them, All was in their power now, advices them to determine their ſeveral fates, according to their demerits, one by one; this they readily hearkened to; and as they paſs'd a doom upon any one, he approved the Sentence; but before the Execution, he perſwades them to bethink themſelves of another and a better man to be in his room, ſince a Senate they could not be without; but here the buſineſs ſtuck, as he had foreſeen it would; the People who agreed unanimouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt the old Senator, could by no means agree who ſhould ſucceed; one named this man, another that, but whoever was
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:105495:90"/>
named by one Party, was ſure to be rejected by another; that in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion as great a pique as they had received againſt the old Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, for want of agreement in better men to come in their room, they unanimouſly concluded it beſt to keep the old ones in. Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi> left his ſtory to the Reader to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, and ſo do I.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi>'s Fourthly runs thus; <hi>I never yet met with any argument (that I can call to mind) for the abſolute inforcing of ſome particular</hi> needleſs <hi>ceremonies to be obſerved in the Church, by all who live under one Civil government, but what could be of the ſame force, if it were applyed to all the Churches in the world: There is as much reaſon (I think) that every Church and Congregation for the ſervice of God throughout the world, ſhould obſerve the ſame ceremonies, as that all the Congregations in one Nation ſhould.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:105495:90"/>1. I ſhall not here ſtand to enquire how far this doth (<hi>in hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſi</hi> at leaſt) violate the 27th Canon, which forbids and cenſures all ſpeaking againſt his Majeſties Authority in maters Eccleſiaſtical; or whether this doth not (in the ſame manner) clap the brand of PERJURY, (ſo far as he is able) upon all Parliaments, who in the Oath of Allegiance and Supremacy (which they are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to take before they can ſit in Parliament) do aſſert the Kings Authority in matters Eccleſiaſtical thus, <hi>That he is Supream Moderator and Governour in all cauſes, and over all perſons, as well</hi> Eccleſiaſtical <hi>as Civil, in theſe his Majeſties Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions</hi> [and no other.] Whereas if the King have no more power to inforce particular Ceremonies on all who live under the ſame Civil Government of <hi>England,</hi> than he has to enforce it on thoſe of <hi>Germany, France, Spain,</hi> and other Churches; he is ſo far from being
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:105495:91"/>
the Supream Head and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, or having the ſupream pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in all cauſes Eccleſiaſtical, that in all ſuch cauſes within theſe his Dominions, he hath no power at all.</p>
               <p>And as in the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> ſo in all other reformed Churches, there is the ſame power among themſelves, and no other: As the Churches of the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Confeſſion,<note place="margin">Dure's vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciae.</note> give the Sacrament to none, but kneeling; the <hi>Geneva</hi> Churches, and the Proteſtant Churches of <hi>France,</hi> give it to none but thoſe that ſtand in the act of receiving; and the like ceremonies there are inforced up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all that live in thoſe Churches under one and the ſame Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. But</p>
               <p n="2">2. I think it ſufficient anſwer to this, to tell Mr. <hi>Bolde,</hi> that there would be the ſame reaſon for every Church throughout the world to obſerve the ſame ceremonies, as
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:105495:91"/>
for all the Congregations in one Nation, in caſe they were all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joined by the ſame or alike Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi> doth ſeem to bound and limit his aforeſaid aſſertion with this Parentheſis, <hi>(if we reſpect only the obſervations and reflections that Heathens and the like will make, when they ſee that in one and the ſame Nation, people profeſſing the ſame Religion, do ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve different rites) as he ſuppoſeth Heathens and the like enemies of Chriſtianity to do, on the account of Chriſtians of different Nations, obſerving different rites:</hi> Which groundleſs ſuppoſal is all he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth to confirm and ſtrengthen his 4th bold aſſertion: Now to ſee how impertinently this is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged,</p>
               <p n="1">1. No Church-ceremonies are inforced or not inforced among Chriſtians upon any ſuch conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or in any ſuch regard to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:105495:92"/>
Heathens, as his Reaſon doth ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Heathens and the like ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Chriſtianity cannot reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably make any ſuch obſervations, reflexions and exceptions on our holy faith, on the account of our obſerving the ſame or different rites in Gods ſervice, as the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon he renders doth ſuppoſe. And therefore is very frivolouſly and impertinently render'd.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi>'s Fifthly runs thus; <hi>Long and often experience hath made it undeniably evident, that putttng the paenal Laws rigorouſly in execution againſt humble, modeſt, conſcientious Diſſenters (and I plead for none but ſuch) has not anſwered the deſign for which they were inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded — Severity (ſays he) is not a proper method for the ſatisfying of mens judgements, or the removing of their ſcruples;</hi> with much more to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:105495:92"/>When <hi>Vincentius</hi> ſeemed to argue thus in behalf of the Diſſenters of St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>'s time; St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>'s Anſwer was, <hi>Nunquid ideo negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genda eſt medicina, quia nonnullo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum inſanabilis eſt peſtilentia? what then (ſays he) is medicine therefore to be neglected, becauſe ſome mens plague is incurable?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ep. <hi>48.</hi> Litt. I. K. L.</note> 
                  <hi>It is better to love with ſeverity, than to deceive with lenity: Do you think</hi> (ſays that Father) <hi>that none are to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled when the master of the Family ſaid,</hi> 14 Luke, Compel them to come in, that my houſe may be full; <hi>and that he admired with great thankfulneſs, that they (the Donatiſts) who could by no other means be brought to think of a change for the better,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lit. H.</note> 
                  <hi>yet when once affrighted with the terrour of the Laws, ſet their hearts ſeriouſly to conſider the truth, leſt if they ſhould ſuffer puniſhment not for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, but ſtubbornneſs ſake, their patience would be fruitleſs and vain, and leſt they ſhould afterwards find
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:105495:93"/>
no other reward from God, than what was due to wickedneſs: And a tolerating of them, he there calls a rendering evil for evil,</hi> verè ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum pro malo redderemus <hi>(ſays he)</hi> And in the ſame letter of the ſame Epiſtle, <hi>O that I could ſhew</hi> (ſays he) <hi>how many of thoſe</hi> Circumcellians, [i. e. <hi>the worſt ſort of Donatiſts,] are now become good Chriſtians, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning their former error, whereby they taught whatever they did through their unquiet raſhneſs, was for the Church, (or glory) of God; who had never been brought to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſoundneſs of belief, unleſs they had been bound, like mad men, with the Cords of thoſe very laws which you find fault with:</hi> And here it is to be remarked of the Donatiſt-Diſſenters of old, and of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Diſſenters of late,</p>
               <p n="2">2. What ill uſe they always made of Toleration and Power, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they attained it: While <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:105495:93"/>
was Emperor, none pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioned and pleaded more for Toleration than the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> and declared themſelves utter enemies to any perſon or principle that was for diſturbing or puniſhing men for conſcience ſake: But as ſoon as <hi>Julian</hi> was ſetled in the Empire, and (with a deſign of root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out Chriſtianity) countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the Donatiſts, gave them To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration, and at laſt reſtored the Churches to them: that Apoſtate Emperor himſelf was not ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perious, ſo tyrannical and ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary as they. In like manner the Modern Diſſenters (as Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi> ſays of the contrary) <hi>long and often experience</hi> has made it evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that the toleration which they lately enjoyed, made them as imperious as ever the Laws would ſuffer, eſpecially in 81, and 82; when a Conforming Miniſter (as I am credibly informed) could ſcarce walk <hi>London</hi> Streets with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:105495:94"/>
ſome open affront offer'd him by that Party. But when they had the power in the Uſurpation-times, let who will read <hi>Mercurius Ruſticus,</hi> and the like Books, and he ſhall find their barbarous cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty in Perſecuting, ſcarce exceeded by the <hi>Mari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> Perſecution. They inflicted cenſures for a meer ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picion of covetouſneſs, for dancing at a Wedding for a ſuperfluity in Raiment, for fetching a little water on the Lords day to boil a Pot, or waſh ones hands, though not twenty Yards diſtant from their Houſes: Whereas the mild and wholſome Laws againſt Diſſenters are executed on them for crimes of another nature, for Sedition in the State, which, <hi>as long and often experience has made undeniably evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,</hi> has always accompanied Schiſm in the Church.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But why doth Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi> call it ſeverity, and (as in his Sermon)
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:105495:94"/>
                  <hi>Perſecution?</hi> Did the King treat them as thoſe of their principle do in <hi>New England,</hi> ſuch as diſſent from them, with baniſhment and death. The Independents of <hi>New England</hi> impoſe a penalty of five ſhillings a day on all that come not to hear their Sermons; they baniſh all the <hi>Antinomians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Thornd.</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance of Penalties.</note> and put the Quakers to death: Or were they treated by us, as we are by Papiſts, with a <hi>go ye curſed, ſending them to Hell</hi> with <hi>Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma's,</hi> for meer inconformity and no more? then indeed one may talk of ſeverity or perſecution ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and plead for Moderation towards Diſſenters. But inſtead of this, our Church calls them Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and treats them like ſuch. The King indulged to them as great a Toleration as many of them would deſire, till the fruit of it appeared in a barbarous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy againſt his Life and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. I ſay the <hi>Fruit</hi> of it;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Anno</hi> 1683.</note>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:105495:95"/>
for it's impoſſible to apprehend how ſuch a Conſpiracy ſhould be contrived and carryed on with any hopes of ſucceſs, without ſtrong preſumption and confident expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of help and ſtrength from the Diſſenting Proteſtants; which makes it evident and certain, that though the generality of Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters be acquitted from ſo much as knowing any thing of the Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous deſign, yet it cannot be denied, but that it is eventually, and <hi>per accidens</hi> (at leaſt) the effect and product of the Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformity; and this will appear to be undeniably, true by this <hi>Dilemma.</hi> This Conſpiracy in 83<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> was contrived and carried on either with hopes of ſucceſs, or without hopes of ſucceſs; without hopes of ſucceſs, no ſuch conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy ever was, (or can poſſibly be imagined ever to be) contrived and carried on: With hopes of ſucceſs this could not be, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:105495:95"/>
expectation (if not grand aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of help and ſtrength from the Diſſenting Party; for no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Party could afford them any help conſiderable. And to ſay, that any Church-of-<hi>England</hi> man were, or poſſibly could be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in it, is that moſt ſenceleſs of all abſurdities [a contradiction in the terms]; for a Church-of-<hi>England</hi> man he cannot be, who is not well affected to the King, the Church, and the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Now is it not a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction to ſay, that a Perſon or Party well affected to the King, ſhould be in ſuch a Helliſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy againſt him? that one well affected to the Church and the Government, ſhould be in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy againſt the Church and Government? If it be ſaid the Conſpirators came to Church, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Sacrament, obſerved the Ceremonies and Orders of the Church; why this would argue
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:105495:96"/>
their greater hypocriſy, and the more dangerouſneſs of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but would be concluſive of nothing againſt the <hi>Dilemma:</hi> Which makes it as clear and plain as any firſt principle, That the late Phanatick Plot in 83, was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventually (at leaſt) the effect of Nonconformity: This I ſay can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be denied, though it ſhould be granted, that not one Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſt in <hi>England</hi> ſo much as knew of it till the publick diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery.</p>
               <p>So that whereas Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi> talks of the <hi>rigorous execution of penal Laws not anſwering the end and deſign they were intended for;</hi> it's evident from hence, that ſo far as not putting the Laws in ſuch execution on Diſſenters doth mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to the increaſe of their Party; ſo far it doth gratify and miniſter to the deſigns of Phana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Conſpirators, though the Diſſenters were ever ſo innocent,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:105495:96"/>
and as great haters of ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy as the moſt loyal Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts whatever.</p>
               <p>But the main thing that Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi> inſiſts on in this place, is this, <hi>that the rigorous execution of the poenal Laws doth not anſwer the end it was intended for;</hi> (which is ſuppreſſing Nonconformity) but doth rather incourage the thing, and increaſe the Party: For this he appeals to <hi>long and often experience;</hi> and this he aſſerts at large, with the greateſt aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance imaginable. Whereas 1ſt, <hi>in ſtatu quo,</hi> the thing is yet <hi>ſub judice,</hi> the event ſcarcely yet diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernable, the effect yet ſcarcely known, becauſe ſince Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeths</hi> reign, the Laws have not been put into rigorous execution till this laſt year. When Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi> wrote his Book, the rigorous exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the Law was much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laxed, and it was the relaxation that ſo increaſed the Party: Our
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:105495:97"/>
State-Phyſitians have found it ſo, that that peſtilent Lax, was the true morbifick cauſe of that dangerous ſuperfaetation in the Body politick. And let <hi>Bolde</hi> Quacklings pretend what they will, <hi>Perilis in ſua cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſque arte credendum eſt;</hi> and thus as to the preſent or late ſtate of things.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If we look back on former times, <hi>Long and often experience has made it undeniably evident, that putting the paenal Laws rigorouſly in execution againſt Diſſenters, hath anſwered the end for which they were deſigned. i. e.</hi> Hath ſuppreſſed Diſſenters, and reformed Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, when nothing elſe would do.<note place="margin">Hiſt. of Presb. lib. <hi>9.</hi> n. <hi>25, 27.</hi>
                  </note> In Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign, it was enacted in Parliament, <hi>That whoſoever ſhould be found at any Conventicle or private meeting on pretence of Religious exerciſe, were to ſuffer impriſonment, or to depart the Realm, never to return without leave firſt granted,</hi> and the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:105495:97"/>
failure herein was made Felony: And it was ſuch ſharp Laws made againſt them, and rigorouſly exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted on them, that utterly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd them, and thereby effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally promoted the peace and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility of Church and State, when all other means failed; and that it was K. <hi>James</hi>'s relaxing this rigour that firſt revived their faction, is undeniably evident to any that underſtands the Hiſtory of <hi>England</hi> for theſe Hundred and Thirty years laſt paſt.</p>
               <p>And of Old, the whole Hiſtory of the Donatiſts doth make evident, 1. That as the Emperours and their Councils became more zealous for the Chriſtian Religion, their Laws were made more and more ſtrict againſt Diſſenters, and executed with more and more rigour, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the growth and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of their zeal for Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. And 2dly, that putting the Laws rigorouſly in execution, was
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:105495:98"/>
the only thing that reſtrained that dangerous faction, and reſtored peace and unity to the Church: <hi>Mine own City</hi> (ſays St. <hi>Auguſtine) which was once all</hi> Donatiſts,<note place="margin">Civitas mea cum tota eſſet in parte Donati ad unitatem Cathol. timore legum imperialium con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſa eſt. Ep. <hi>48.</hi> lit. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>. X.</note> 
                  <hi>is now converted to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Church by [this very means]</hi> the terror of the Imperial Laws: <hi>The terror of the Laws was ſo profitable to them,</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that they did bleſs God for them, ſaying, God be thanked that hath quickened us,</hi> ſtimulo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roris, <hi>by the terror of the Laws, to ſeek and to find the truth. Others</hi> (ſays he) <hi>ſay we were frigheed by falſe rumours, from entering into the Church, which we ſhould never have known to be falſe, if we had not come to the Church; and we ſhould never have come to it, if we had not been compelled:</hi> And in his 50th Epiſtle to <hi>Bonifacius,</hi> They who formerly had been on the Donatiſts Party, <hi>thanked God, that now by
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:105495:98"/>
the correction of the Laws they are delivered from that</hi> fur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, <hi>as he calls their Nonconformity; and that they who did ſo hate the Laws, do now love them, and rejoice in the cure that they had made on them, as formerly they did in their mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs deteſt the wholſome Laws as trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome to them.</hi> He elſewhere calls them mad that divide the Church, and would have them like mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men tyed and bound with the Chain of wholſome Laws and Severities:<note place="margin">Contra hos Imperator <hi>(Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtan.)</hi> lege ſancivit, auferri eorum oratoria &amp; Eccleſiis ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicari &amp; neque in domiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s privatorum eos Congregationes, neque publice celebrare, ſed in Eccleſia Cathol communicare &amp; in eam cunctis convenire ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debat, propter quam legem haereſi on m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mor am arb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tror fuiſſe deſtructam. Hiſt. trip. lib. <hi>3</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the firſt Chriſtian Emperour finding the Church divided and diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by Schiſmatick Diſſenters, made a Law againſt them, forbidding and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing all their Conventicles, by which very means (ſays <hi>Sozomen</hi>) the memory of Schiſmaticks was utterly deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And whereas Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi> ſays,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 28.</note>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:105495:99"/>
                  <hi>that ſeverity is not a proper me hod for the ſatisfying of mens judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or removing their ſcruples.</hi> I anſwer, St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſays, that he was once of that mind, and was not for having the Laws rigorouſly executed againſt Diſſenters; but he acknowledges his error in it, and tells us that this opinion of his was conquered and changed <hi>non contradicentium verbis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ep. <hi>48.</hi> lett. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>.</note> 
                  <hi>ſed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrantium exemplis; i e.</hi> as Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi> ſpeaks, by long and often experience. <hi>'Tis true, ſays St.</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,<note place="margin">Let. T.</note> 
                  <hi>none can be made good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his will, but the fear of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering may make him leave off his animoſity againſt the truth; or make him willing to receive the truth which he formerly knew not, and perſiſt in it when he knows it. We know many</hi> (ſays he) <hi>not only ſingle perſons, but whole Cities, that were Donatiſts</hi> (or Separatiſts) <hi>now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come good Catholicks, heartily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted their deviliſh ſeparation, and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:105495:99"/>
fervently loving the unity (and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion) of the Church; all which were made ſuch Conv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s by the fear of thoſe Laws which</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Speaking to Vincentius a Donatiſt.</note> 
                  <hi>you ſo diſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e: And theſe examples propounded to me by my Colleague, made me change my opinion: For ſaith he, I was once of that opinion, that no m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n ought to be comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lled to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ty of the Church but that this was to be done only by force of</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rbo agendum diſputatione pugnandum ratione vincen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum.</note> 
                  <hi>argumen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, that they were to be convict by Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, not compelled by Law; for this I thought could do no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hing but make open Schiſmaticks,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Litt. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>.</note> 
                  <hi>or counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit Catholicks; but this I was convinced to be an error</hi> non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicentium verbis, ſed demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrantium exemplis, <hi>by long and often experience.</hi> And therefore the Holy Father in his Epiſtles to <hi>Bonifacius, Januarius, Feſtus</hi> and others, doth mightily preſs the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous execution of the Imperial
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:105495:100"/>
Laws againſt Diſſenters, not only at that which is neceſſary to the unity and ſafety of the Church, but of ſufficient tendency <hi>to ſatisfy m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns judgments, and remove their ſcruples,</hi> by compelling them to the moſt apt and proper means of that ſatisfaction and removal: But ſuppoſe that it were not as the venerable St. <hi>Augustine</hi> ſays, but as Mr <hi>Bold</hi> ſays, that ſeverity is not <hi>a proper means to ſatisfy mens judgments, or remove their ſcruples:</hi> Yet,</p>
               <p n="2">2. It cannot be denyed, but that it is a proper means to preſerve the Churches unity; and therefore <hi>Constantine</hi> the moſt Religious Emperour, the firſt that ever made Laws againſt Diſſenters, did not ſeek to bring the Heathens to Chriſtianity by ſeverity and force; but by ſeverity and force he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to keep the Chriſtians in unity, and to that end enacted
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:105495:100"/>
many ſevere Laws againſt the Diſſenters of thoſe times; ſuch ſays <hi>Augustine</hi> as did <hi>in conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis ſuis ſeparatim congregare.</hi> And 'tis remarkable, that though the Laws made againſt thoſe Donatiſt-Diſſenters, were not only great pecuniary mulcts, but baniſhment, and ſeizing their Goods for the Emperours uſe, as I underſtand thoſe words ut <hi>fiſco vin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>icarentur;</hi> yet doth the holy Father account theſe laws ſo favourable, as not to puniſh but admoniſh only;<note place="margin">Lit. O.</note> and having ſpoke of the Paganiſh Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters being puniſhed with death for their Id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>latry, as that ſeve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ity which the Orthodox and Donatiſts both did approve of and rejoice in; he adds,<note place="margin">Lit. O. P.</note> that the wickedneſs of Schiſm is worſe than that of Idolatry; which is a broad intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that that holy man thought Schiſm a Capital crime.</p>
               <p>And here I cannot but take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of his calling the wholſome
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:105495:101"/>
execution of the Poenal Laws, by the odious name of <hi>Perſecution,</hi> and not only ſo, but like the <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists</hi> of old, and the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> of late, doth wreſt and rack the holy Scripture, to make it ſpeak its ſence of it: Witneſs that very Text on which he preached his printed Sermon, <hi>Gal</hi> 4 29. <hi>As he that was born after the fleſh, perſecuted him that was born after the Spirit, ſo it is now,</hi> where the Apoſtle doth plainly make the party proſecuting, to be the party perſecuted: It was <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Sarah</hi> that corrected <hi>Hagar</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael</hi> and yet (ſays the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle) <hi>Iſhmael</hi> he that was born after the fleſh, was the party perſecuting, tho the party ſuffering <hi>By which we may underſtand</hi> (ſays St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> upon the place) <hi>that the Church rather ſuffers perſecution by the pride and wickedneſs of carnal men,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ep <hi>48.</hi> Lit. L.</note> [by their <hi>Iſhmaeli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſh</hi> reproaches] <hi>when ſhe endeavours to amend them by temporal puniſhments and correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, than they by the Church; ſo that
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:105495:101"/>
whatever the true Mother doth in this caſe, though it may ſeem harſh and bitter, yet ſhe doth not render evil for evil, but endeavour by whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome diſcipline to expel ſin; not out of hatred or deſire to hurt, but out of love to cure:</hi> Whereby it doth plainly appear, that the execution of the poenal Laws againſt Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters (for of ſuch he ſpeaks) is ſo far from being Perſecution, that in that caſe, the party <hi>Proſecuting</hi> is the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>Perſecuted</hi> [with <hi>Iſhmaelitiſh</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, as being <hi>Perſecutors,</hi> &amp;c] But the beſt account of the true notion of <hi>Perſecution,</hi> is in the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Dr <hi>Hick</hi>'s Sermon of Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and thither I refer the Reader.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi>'s 6th Argument is no more than this; <hi>It was never known that any Indifferent Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies were univerſally impoſed in a knowing age, and the opinions of all good men did agree to them</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which is no more in effect, than if he had ſaid, That becauſe ſome
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:105495:102"/>
good men have not agreed to the uſe of ſome Ceremonies, therefore the Church muſt proſtitute her authority to every Sceptick Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vator in altering her ancient Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions.</p>
               <p n="7">7. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 7th and laſt is taken from <hi>our condeſcentions to the Papists in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> our Rubrick, Publick Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and Articles, in order to the bringing of the Papists to join with us in our worſhip</hi> &amp;c. <hi>He inſtance in the Churches expunging that paſſage in the Littany, where we prayed to be delivered from the tyranny and all the deteſtable enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of the Biſhops of</hi> Rome, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis true, that for the firſt Eighteen years of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> few of the Popiſh Recuſants abſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves from our Churches, till Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the Fifth, by his interdictory Bull would have all communion with us renounced;
<pb facs="tcp:105495:102"/>
and in meer hopes of uniting and bringing them over to the Reformed Religion, there was that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcention and compliance made; and the like and greater conceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were indulged (or offer'd at leaſt) to the Nonconformiſts in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, till it did appear that they would be ſatisfied with no other conceſſions, than what were judged inconſiſtent with the ſafety of Church and State.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Bold</hi> having finiſhed his Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Arguments againſt Impoſition of Church-Ceremonies, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of poenal Laws, has this one Story more, that <hi>when the Emperour took a Biſhop in compleat Armour, he ſent the Armour to the Pope, with this word,</hi> haeccine ſunt veſtes Filii tui?</p>
               <p>Whereby Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi> would inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate again (as the Precedent
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:105495:103"/>
words ſhew) that only Arguments and Reaſons, and not coercive means, are to be uſed with Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
               <p>The error of this hath its refutal from ſome of my laſt Citations out of St. <hi>Augustine:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ep. <hi>48.</hi> Litt. T.</note> And therefore no more but to return the Story: <hi>Paulus Emilius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Val. Max.</note> a Noble General, when ſeveral of his Souldiers took on them to preſcribe and ſuggeſt to him their ſeveral models of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement and diſcipline, <hi>Acuite vos gladios</hi> (ſays the General) <hi>mind you your Swords, and your buſineſs, be ready to obey, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute what ſhall be commanded you, but leave the diſcipline and manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of affairs to me your General: q. d.</hi> let Governours and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment alone, keep you your ſtation, and mind your buſineſs in oppoſing the Enemy, and obeying your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, but do not dare to medle with controlling, directing or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:105495:103"/>
to thoſe whom it is your buſineſs to obey. But if theſe bold Soldiers that preſcribed thus ſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cily to their General, ſhould have turn'd <hi>Runagadoes,</hi> and been caught by him [like this Pleader with his Militant Apologies for Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Enemies,] going over into the Enemies Camp, no doubt but he would have given them the very edge of Martial Law.</p>
               <p>Thus have I faithfully remarked all that I judge any thing argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentative in Mr. <hi>Bolde</hi>'s fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Plea; which is indeed nothing elſe but arrogant dogmatizing and preſcribing to Superiours [inſtead of <hi>Pleading</hi>] for licentious and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly Toleration [on pretence of <hi>Moderation</hi>] of the ſworn ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Church and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, [under the name of Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters] I ſee little elſe in his Book, but what is fairly reducible to one of theſe heads, Impertinency
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:105495:104"/>
or Scandal; of the former ſort is his ſpending ſo many Pages in telling who they are he pleads for; <hi>they are</hi> (ſays he) <hi>more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, men of ſuch Learning</hi> as Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hickman,</hi> &amp;c. Mr. <hi>Hickman</hi> I know not; Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Learning no honeſt man will envy: He muſt be acknowledged a Learned man: If he had not skill in fencing, he could not be ſo quarrelſom. <hi>Arrius</hi> was ſtiled <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, was accounted the moſt logical, and one of the moſt learned in his time: But what of that? The Orthodox Biſhops thought him never the more fit for Church-toleration or comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: But ſpeaking of Impertinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, the very name forbids me inſiſting on the thing.</p>
               <p>And ſo of his ſcandals alſo, which are ſo deteſtable and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, that it were a ſcandal to publiſh but the rehearſal of them;
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:105495:104"/>
witneſs the Story of the Regiſter, <hi>p.</hi> 40, which for its ſcandalous reflections on the Eccleſiaſtical Government, there's nothing in <hi>Martin Mar-Prelate; H'ye any work for the Cooper, or the Cobler of</hi> Glouceſter, can exceed. So of thoſe whom he charges with ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting [as the Reader muſt compute it] Sixteen or Seventeen Hours together in a Tavern or an Ale-houſe, <hi>p</hi> 19. His fraudulent ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions touching the great evil of impoſing Church-ceremonies; with many the like, which run through his Book, like a vein through his Body; and which I cannot repeat without ſin and ſhame: Or if I could that, It would even tire an indefatiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Reader to lead him through all the dark and dirty Labyrinth of his defamatory Libel.</p>
               <p>I muſt therefore be abrupt in this Appeal to the Reader; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:105495:105"/>
it be not the part of a moſt abominable <hi>Church-Traytor,</hi> to play the <hi>CHAM</hi> with the Church, in ſuch a treacherous and deceitful manner.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:105495:105"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
